<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The chief interest of man, or, A discourse of religion, clearly demonstrating the equity of the precepts of the Gospel, and how much the due observance thereof doth conduce to the happiness and well-being as well of humane societies as of particular persons by H. Lukin.</title>
            <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1665</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 102 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49459</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3473</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R125</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11871469</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11871469</idno>
            <idno type="VID">50143</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49459)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50143)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 501:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The chief interest of man, or, A discourse of religion, clearly demonstrating the equity of the precepts of the Gospel, and how much the due observance thereof doth conduce to the happiness and well-being as well of humane societies as of particular persons by H. Lukin.</title>
                  <author>Lukin, H. (Henry), 1628-1719.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[13], 189, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R.D. for T. Bassett,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1665.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Religion.</term>
               <term>Christianity.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The chief Intereſt of Man;</hi> Or, A Diſcourſe of RELIGION, Clearly demonſtrating The Equity of the Precepts of the Goſpel, and how much the due Obſervance thereof doth conduce to the happineſs and well-being as well of Humane Societies, As of Particular Perſons.</p>
            <p>By <hi>H. Lukin.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Suffer me a little, and I will ſhew thee what I have yet to ſpeak on Gods behalf, <bibl>
                  <hi>Job</hi> 36.2.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>Dicam ego quid ſentiam dicent fortè meliora do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiores. <bibl>
                  <hi>Aug. contra Fauſtum.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>R.D.</hi> for <hi>T. Baſsett</hi> under S. <hi>Dunſtans</hi> Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1665.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Mongſt ſo many books wherewith the World is fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, it may juſtly be expected, that none ſhould obtrude more upon it, without giving a fair ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count thereof, unleſs they have attained to that repute for Wiſdom which <hi>Job</hi> had, <hi>chap. 29.21.</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that men give ear, and wait, and keep ſilence at their counſel, waiting for it as for the rain, &amp; opening their mouth wide as for the latter rain:</hi> ſuch need no Apology to
<pb facs="tcp:50143:3"/>beſpeak a reception of their Labors, but it is far from me to reckon my ſelf of that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, <hi>haud equidem tali me dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor honore,</hi> yet I muſt confeſs it is not much that I have to ſay in my own defence. The perſwaſion of Friends, from an opinion of the uſefulneſſe of ſuch Books as Men publiſh, is ſuch a common Apology, that the world grows weary of it; if I ſhould ſay that <hi>ſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bunt indocti doctique</hi> was an old obſervation, ſo that it is no new thing for Men of ſmall Learning to write Books, it might well be retorted that the World hath ſuffered ſo much by ſuch Mens Writings,
<pb facs="tcp:50143:3"/>that it is pity they ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer any more by them. It will be but a poor Plea to ſay that I have written but little, and ſo ſhall put Men to the expence of very little time or money for the reading of it, if the little which I have written may not probably be of ſome advantage to the World; but, this, through the bleſſing of God, I am not without hopes of, if one ſinner might hereby be converted from the error of his way, I ſhould account it an happy fruit, and abundant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of my well intended endeavors; but if the diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient may not be hereby turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Wiſdom of the juſt,
<pb facs="tcp:50143:4"/>yet I hope the children of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom will hereby be eſtabliſhed and encouraged to hold faſt their integrity, &amp; be furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with that, wherewith they may put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh Men. If the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopians</hi> paint Angels black, and Devils white, becauſe they are black themſelves, &amp; Pride themſelves in it, as their beauty, this makes not us to diſlike our own complexion, neither can they perſwade us to waſh our ſelves with Ink, that we may be like them. If therefore ſome Men glory in their ſhame, and account it their honour to be like the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, or hate holineſſe, wherein
<pb facs="tcp:50143:4"/>Men do moſt reſemble God, and bear his Image, as it is ſaid of the <hi>Baſilisk,</hi> that its enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Man is ſuch, that it will fly with rage upon the Picture of a Man, let not this be a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation to us, to learn their wayes, <hi>let them return to us, let us not return to them, Jer. 15.19.</hi> If our adverſary ſhould write a Book againſt us, (that I may allude to the words of <hi>Job,</hi> c. <hi>31.35. &amp;c.</hi>) if it be of ſcorns and reproaches, let us bind it to us as a Crown, and ſay as <hi>David, 2 Sam. 6.21. I will yet be more vile,</hi> if to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God, and be like to him, be to be vile: but if he will en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter us in good earneſt,
<pb facs="tcp:50143:5"/>with ſerious arguments, let us go near to him as a Prince, and not fear, having all the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that can be drawn from the authority of our Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord and Law-giver, from our own intereſt, from equity, ingenuity and grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, on our ſide.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not be very ſollicitous or induſtrious to decline or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipate the cenſures of others, I know it is ordinarily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, that Men of no name that have not that real worth which may make others take notice of them, have that pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſign in publiſhing ſuch things as are more admired by themſelves, than by any body
<pb facs="tcp:50143:5"/>elſe to get themſelves a name, and to make themſelves and their own ſuppoſed worth known to the World. Let Men think of me as they pleaſe; I hope there is none ſhall think more meanly of me, than I do of my ſelf, and I am ſuch an impartial judge of my own la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors, that I am ſo far from projecting thereby for any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem or credit in the World, that I ſhould rather if that were my aim and deſign, have held my peace, which is the way for a fool to be counted wiſe, <hi>Prov. 17.28.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One thing I would advertiſe the Reader of, that this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe was finiſhed in another
<pb facs="tcp:50143:6"/>Nation, after ſome years obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations, of the lives &amp; man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſuch as in other parts of the World profeſs Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, both <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants,</hi> the manner of whoſe converſation I was then better acquainted with, than of thoſe of our own Nation, which I hope may ſuffice to free me from all ſuſpicion of having any oblique aſpect upon parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, or any particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſort of men, or of calcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting this Treatiſe only for our own Meridian, and for our own times. I know, were it in other Languages, it might indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently ſerve for any place where the Goſpel hath been
<pb facs="tcp:50143:6"/>Preached, and might have had its uſe in the pureſt times, which have been ſince the Chriſtian name was known: that little I have ſeen of the World, will eaſily keep me from judging our own Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the worſt of any that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs Religon, unleſs the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges which we enjoy above others, do raiſe our guilt to a greater height; and I am not ſo unacquainted with the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of former Ages, as being ſurprized to cry out, <hi>O tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra! O mores!</hi> or to make that unwiſe enquiry, <hi>Eccleſ. 7.10. what is the cauſe that the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer dayes were better than theſe?</hi> I confeſs I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb facs="tcp:50143:7"/>been in <hi>Pauls</hi> caſe, <hi>Act. 17.16.</hi> when I have obſerved amongst the generality of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in all places, ſo much difference betwixt mens prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples &amp; practices, &amp; ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny profeſſing to know God, which in works deny him, &amp; this hath made me ſometimes expreſs my ſelf with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er paſſion and vehemency, as knowing the terror of the Lord, and grieved to ſee the miſery that ſo many without repentance are haſtning to: for thougb I owe a ſpecial love to thoſe of the houſehold of faith, yet I profeſs my ſelf a Citizen of the univerſe, and ſo have a charity and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion towards all.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50143:7"/>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECTION. I. <hi>The</hi> Practical Atheiſt <hi>a greater wonder than the</hi> Specula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Atheiſt; <hi>the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſs of ſuch as profeſſing Religion, do yet neglect the commands thereof, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe ſuch as deſire to be found in a ſtrict obſervance of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Spartan</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to hear an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of <hi>Hercules,</hi> replyed, <hi>Ecquis eum vituperat?</hi> Doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny body ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him? and ſome will think I might <hi>periturae parcere chartae,</hi> or rather better in ploy precious ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>revocable
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50143:8"/>hours than in Apologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing for that which needs no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and which there is ſuch a reverence of ſo deeply implanted in every Mans nature; but upon a nearer approach and exact ſurvey of things, we ſhall find there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the World doth either need or deſerve a more ſerions conſideration and juſt defence. <hi>The Speculative Atheiſt</hi> is ſuch a Monſter that many will hardly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of ſuch a thing in nature. And it ſeems incredible to them that any ſhould doubt of a <hi>Deity;</hi> yet daily experience and obſervation refutes our more rational and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired Speculations, and hath put many Learned Men to the labour of proving that there is a God; this being the utmoſt we are able in the Theory to make good; <hi>That there are none think that there is no God, but ſuch as for whom it were well if there were none:</hi> and theſe being judicially given up to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by their own luſts, firſt, think it would be well for them if there were no God, finding his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:50143:8"/>croſſing their Carnal inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts and corrupt deſires; thence they proceed to wiſh there were no God, and by degrees arrive at flat <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> inordinate paſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting <hi>Deſire</hi> into <hi>Opinion</hi> (as we eaſily believe that which we ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly deſire) that ſo having baf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fled their Judgments, and drawn them into the ſame confederacy with their Luſts, they may ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their control or contradiction, and avoid the reproofs of their Conſciences while they give up themſelves freely to ſatisfie their vile affections. <hi>His gradibus itur.</hi> I affirm the <hi>Practical Atheiſt</hi> is yet a greater wonder, and a more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid Monſter than the <hi>Speculative A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſt.</hi> (As <hi>Mirandula</hi> hath well obſerved) <hi>it is a wonder that any ſhould doubt of the truth of the Goſpel after ſo many evident proofs of it; but a greater wonder that any ſhould believe it, and yet live as if it were not true.</hi> But <hi>Affrica</hi> hath not ſo many monſters in nature as <hi>Europe</hi> hath in <hi>Religion,</hi> How many thouſands of Zealots have we that profeſſe the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50143:9"/>name of Chriſt, and preſume vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently that they ſhall be ſaved by him, yet look into their converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and you would not believe their own mouths, or imagine that they are ſeriouſly perſwaded that there is a God, an Heaven, an Hell, a Judgment to come where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſhall be ſentenced to their everlaſting home.</p>
               <p>Nay, hear O Heavens and be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhed, O Earth, hath any people dealt ſo with their Gods, which are yet no Gods, as Chriſtians deal with Chriſt? Do Turks deal ſo with their <hi>Mahomet?</hi> Do they ſcorn thoſe that are moſt careful to obſerve the Rules of his <hi>Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran?</hi> Are they aſhamed to be ſeen to have any reſpect to his Laws? Yet I call Heaven and Earth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord againſt Chriſtians, that <hi>he that turns from his wickedneſſe, makes himſelf a prey,</hi> yea, as <hi>Salvian</hi> complained of old, <hi>Mali eſſe coguntur ne viles habeantur.</hi> Men are fain to turn Rebels a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Chriſt and caſt off the fear of his commands to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50143:9"/>from the ſcorn and hatred of Chriſtians, amongſt whom he muſt go for a Melancholick dull ſot, or ſneaking fool, and one that hath nothing of generoſity that dare not ſet his mouth againſt Heaven, or defie the authority of his Maker; inſomuch that he that cannot harden himſelf againſt ſcorn, ſhall be jeared out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; he ſhall forfeit the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his breeding, that ſhall ſpeak a word of the Scriptures; he ſhall paſſe for a ſilly fellow that will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon the pleaſures of Sin in hopes of an unſeen-Glory, and he ſhall be accounted importunate or uncivil that ſhall interrupt Mens carnal mirth by caſting in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful mention of God or his commands, and be thought unſit for the company of Perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and breeding. Of old they accounted it the ſum and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Religion <hi>to imitate him whom they worſhipped.</hi> Thoſe that adored mortal Deities (ſuch as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> and <hi>Caeſar</hi>) were ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious to imitate their <hi>Vertues,</hi> yea,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50143:10"/>ſome Emperors have been imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by their flattering Courtiers in their <hi>Defects</hi> and <hi>Deformities.</hi> The holineſſe of God is his Glory, and (of all his attributes) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to us for our imitation, ſee 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Exod.</hi> 15.17. and compare <hi>Iſa.</hi> 16.3. with <hi>John</hi> 12.40. and yet how do men <hi>glory</hi> in their <hi>ſhame,</hi> while they are <hi>aſhamed</hi> of their <hi>glory? Phil.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.36. but that ſome are wiſer than to be ſo befooled out of Heaven, holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe would be hiſſed out of the World.</p>
               <p>How many think it a greater reproach to call one a Saint than a Drunkard, a Whoremongen or whatever is evil, When the Scripture makes this a title of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, and that from whence they are ſo denominated abſolutely ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation? O let not theſe things be told in <hi>Gath,</hi> or publiſhed in <hi>Aſhkelon.</hi> Let not Turks and Heathens hear ſuch things of Chriſtians. What God dowe worſhip? What Saviour do we own? Are they like the Idols
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:50143:10"/>of the Heathens who (as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid of old) <hi>are worſhipped in vain, and may be abuſed at our pleaſure?</hi> Quit your ſelves like Men, awake your reaſon and conſider what I ſhall ſay for God and for his holy Laws, which are (as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith, not only <hi>boly</hi> but <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>good, Rom.</hi> 7.12. So that (as hath been well obſerved by Learned Men) if God had never comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded what he hath done, nor made any tranſcript of the Eternal Law out of the <hi>Idea</hi> of his holy nature; yet, what he hath commanded would have been beſt for Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to obſerve. There is not only an <hi>equity</hi> in them, but they are good <hi>naturally,</hi> as well as <hi>morally,</hi> conducing to the welfare of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, the good of the Univerſe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that if we had ſtood on e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ground with our Maker, and capitulated with him on what terms we would ſubmit our ſelves to him, and what Laws we would be obliged to obſerve, we could not have made conditions more for our own advantage: or if Chriſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50143:11"/>ſhould wave his authority which he hath over us, to <hi>command</hi> us (though the authority of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior is more to be regarded than the advantage of the inferior) he might juſtly <hi>counſel</hi> us, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.18. to obſerve his precepts as that which would be beſt for our ſelves; and if we had no reſpect to his ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraignty, yet regard to our own welfare and happineſſe might ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige us thereto. And having evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the <hi>equity</hi> of the wayes of God, and the benefit Men have thereby, I ſhall endeavour to diſcover and remove the cauſes of this <hi>Practical Atheiſm</hi> that reigns ſo much in the World, and though I know after all I can ſay the Diſeaſe will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe any remedy, yet let me tell all the prophane ſcorners of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe till they can deprive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of reaſon, that is, become beaſts, God and his Saints ſhall have a witneſſe in their breaſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:50143:11"/>
               <head>SECT. II. <hi>The equity of Gods commands: Love (which is the fulfilling of the Law) founded on Gods goodneſs, Patience, Bounty. Fear (which with that obſervance that is the effect of it, is the whole Duty of Man) founded on his Power and Wiſdom:</hi> ratio rei, <hi>or reaſon it ſelf the ground of ſuch things as are of natural right: Gods ſoveraignty the ground of ſuch things as are of poſitive right.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall begin with the <hi>Equity</hi> of Gods commands, and ſhew how reaſonably he requires the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of them, his nature moſt juſtly challenging, and the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of his attributes really me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riting whatſoever his Law exacts as our duty. Man hath (as the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raliſts</hi>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50143:12"/>obſerve) but a <hi>Political</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion over his affections, not ſuch a <hi>deſpotical</hi> and abſolute pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as over his locomotive faculty, and ſo over his outward actions, ſo that he cannot love and hate, and fear, and deſire as he liſt. The Soul being a rational Agent, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it ſelf in reſpect of all Objects according to what it ſees there of <hi>good</hi> or <hi>evil</hi> which begets <hi>liking</hi> or <hi>averſion.</hi> Wherefore <hi>arrogan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> is one of the moſt contemptible vanities amongſt the Sons of men, it being the moſt ridiculous thing in the World for men to require of others that Honour, eſteem, reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, which they have no real worth in themſelves to be a foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of. And it is worſe tyranny than that of the <hi>Egyptian task-Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> who required brick without giving ſtraw. They ſay indeed <hi>honor eſt in honorante</hi> depending on the will of the giver, yet it muſt be <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dically</hi> in him that is honoured, there muſt be a Foundation laid by him, whereon others muſt raiſe their eſteem of him. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50143:12"/>the charge is given to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus, that none ſhould deſpiſe them,</hi> that is, they were to carry themſelves with that gravity, pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, integrity, that none might have occaſion to think meanly and contemptibly of them. Now there is in God a real foundation for all thoſe affections, which he requires of us as the principles of all our outward actions, whereby they are formed and faſhioned. Firſt, God requires that we ſhould <hi>love</hi> him with all our might, with all our ſtrength, with our whole Soul, and this is in effect <hi>the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his commands, the fulfilling of his Law, Love</hi> being the <hi>Queen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regent,</hi> the commanding affection of the Soul, the firſt mover that ſets all on work (as <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith) <hi>Love is the byaſs which turns us where ever we go?</hi> We may judge of the power of this affection by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the effects of it in our ſelves where we do truly <hi>love,</hi> how care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful are we to <hi>pleaſe?</hi> how fearful to <hi>offend?</hi> how deſirous to <hi>enjoy?</hi> how ambitious to <hi>ſerve?</hi> how unweary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:50143:13"/>in <hi>ſerving?</hi> how ready to run <hi>hazards,</hi> to undergo difficulties? what ſympathy is there of all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections? what jealouſie? So that God needs require no more of us, for if he have our <hi>Love,</hi> the reſt will follow. Now it were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming the Majeſty of God to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire this of us, were there not that in his nature, and in his works that did juſtly deſerve it, but there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the creature attractive of our Love which is not eminently in him, <hi>how great is his goodneſs! how great is his beauty?</hi> Zach. 9.17. that is, thoſe perfections of his nature, which being found in the Creature infinitely below what they are in him, make it amiable to us.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Goodneſs</hi> and <hi>greatneſſe</hi> where they meet in <hi>Man</hi> are very <hi>deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> and <hi>lovely,</hi> but <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Optimus Maximus</hi> (as he is wont to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) <hi>the greateſt</hi> and <hi>the beſt,</hi> not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding us more in his <hi>greatneſſe</hi> than in his <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> in his <hi>Glory</hi> than in his <hi>Grace. Mich.</hi> 7.18. What narrow bounds did <hi>Peter</hi> ſet to his forbearance when he asked
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50143:13"/>if he ſhould forgive his brother ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven times? what would ſoon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of us if the forbearance of God were confined within ſuch narrow limits? we indeed paſs by many offences in others becauſe we know not how to revenge them, but God could every moment by a word of his mouth, an act of his will let us know what it is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn his authority. And let us but conſider the diſproportion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and Man, how infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely he is above him, and the nature of God, how holy and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to whatſoever is evil, and we ſhall much more admire his pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and goodneſſe. We can do good to our <hi>Friends,</hi> we who are evil, but to do good to <hi>Enemies</hi> whom we have daily in our power, and who ſtill continue their enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt us is too hard for us. God is <hi>good</hi> to <hi>Angels</hi> that never ſinned, <hi>patient</hi> only to <hi>ſinners.</hi> Let us but recount the various acts of his Providence towards us, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the daily care which he hath of us, the mercies which we daily
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:50143:14"/>receive from him, the evil he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth us from, what offers he makes to us of an eternal Glory with himſelf, what means he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords for obtaining it, how long ſpace of repentance he gives us, and we ſhall find our obligations to him to be infinitely beyond what they are to <hi>Parents, Princes, Friends,</hi> diſloyalty and ingratitude to whom is condemned, abhorred of all. Further <hi>the Fear of God is the whole Duty of Man. Eccl.</hi> 12.13. that is, <hi>efficienter</hi> though not <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliter,</hi> for where ever it is it doth bind the Soul to its duty. <hi>Job.</hi> 28.28. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.7. and I may ſay as much for this as for the Love of God. Methinks it is a condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in him to argue the matter as he doth with ſinners. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.28. when he might let them run upon their own ruine, and know by experience the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger that they deſpiſe. We ſhould deride the threatnings of ſome vain boaſter that ſhould go about to affright us with ſuch things as it were far above his power to ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:50143:14"/>but the frown of a <hi>Caeſar,</hi> an <hi>Alexander</hi> might make us tremble; it is the moſt aſtoniſhing madneſſe and folly in the World for men to account it generoſity &amp; braveneſs of ſpirit, not to be awed by the great words of Scripture, to dare to ſin, to take courage againſt God like the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 4.9. and to account it meanneſs of ſpirit to be affrighted with the threatnings of an inviſible God, whoſe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe we neither ſee nor feel, though it is our own fault, we ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in its effects every day. It is he that hangs the <hi>Earth</hi> on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and when he pleaſeth, makes it tremble, ſends the <hi>Sun</hi> on his errand every day, orders the hoſt of Heaven, making every Star keep its place, thundring with his voice ſo as he can make the Emperors of the World run to hide themſelves, ſetting bounds to the raging waves of the Sea which they dare not paſſe; and though he doth not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day reveal his wrath from Heaven againſt ſinners, yet he hath told us it is not becauſe he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proves
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50143:15"/>of their ways, or knows not how to right himſelf, he only ſtays till the time of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of his righteous judgment, and then he will pour out his wrath like fire and make the ſtouteſt ſinners run, (if it were poſſible for them) un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Rocks and Mountains to hide themſelves from his preſence. <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> were both feared for their <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> and indeed <hi>Wiſdom doth make a Mans face to ſhine,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding reverence and a kind of veneration from others. Now there is none to be compared to God for Wiſdom, he is ſo wiſe he cannot be deceived, cannot be mocked, he ſees through the moſt ſecret deſigns of Men, and laughs them to ſcorn, takes the wiſe in their own craftineſſe, makes thoſe that dare tranſgreſſe his <hi>precepts,</hi> whether they will or no, to fulfil his <hi>purpoſe,</hi> over-reaching them in their moſt cunning contrivan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, making them ſerve his holy ends when they leaſt intend it. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he requires that we ſhould
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:50143:15"/>acknowledge him in all our wayes, owning him as our <hi>Soveraign</hi> in the obſervance of his <hi>precepts,</hi> as our <hi>Preſerver</hi> in depending on his <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence.</hi> And what more juſt and equal, when we had our being from him, when we <hi>live</hi> and <hi>move</hi> in him, when we are daily maintained at his coſt and charges, and are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſent to the <hi>Ox</hi> and the <hi>Aſs</hi> to learn our duty; it being he that gives us all things richly to enjoy, and hath not only <hi>right</hi> and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to <hi>command</hi> us, but <hi>might</hi> and power to <hi>force</hi> us? ſo that if we will do any thing without his leave or <hi>moral</hi> permiſſion, we cannot do it without his <hi>natural</hi> permiſſion. If we run away from his ſervice, he can command the Sea to way-lay us (as in the caſe of <hi>Jonah</hi>) and ſend a Whale to fetch us back. If we would go out of the reach of his Rod, he can make it reach us where ever we go, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in their going to <hi>Egypt, Jer.</hi> 42.16. In ſhort, he commands the boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Winds, the unruly Waves, the Angels that excel in might and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50143:16"/>glory, the Devils that are filled with rage and envy, the Sun, that as a Gyant runs his race, and makes it ſtand ſtill at his pleaſure, the Stars whom he makes as his Hoſt to fight his battels; the frogs, the Flies, the Lice, the Bears, the Lions, the Ravens, as the ſeveral inſtances in holy Scripture ſhew. All theſe are at his beck, and he ſends them at his pleaſure. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate Man only, (for whom he hath done more than for any of the works of his hands, and whom he hath made capable of more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe than the whole viſible Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation) caſts off the authority of his Creator in thoſe things wherein eſpecially it would be his <hi>Wiſdom</hi> to make a <hi>vertue</hi> of <hi>neceſſity;</hi> for when Men will venture upon any thing without asking Gods leave, or taking his counſel, he ſtands by and derides their counſels, and tells them that he is wiſe alſo, and will bring evil upon them, and not call back his word, what he ſaith ſhall be done, none ſhall diſanul it; when their deſigns which they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:50143:16"/>would undertake without him ſhall come to nothing, and they periſh in them. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 31.2. thus God will ſooner or later teach all what it is to deſpiſe his authority or to diſpute his commands. As for our outward actions (what I have already ſaid concerning our internal affections, and thoſe acts and attributes of God whereon they are grounded, being ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) though they ſhould not be of any natural right, or have any intrinſick goodneſſe in them, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tecedently to any command of God concerning them, (which yet doubtleſſe ſome have, and are therefore commanded, becauſe good, as thoſe which are grounded on the precepts of the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) yet as we ſay of the <hi>creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> or the things which we are to believe, though our finite under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings be not able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend the nature and cauſes of ſome of them, yet we have reaſon enough to believe them, becauſe they are ſpoken by him that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not lye; ſo I may ſay of the <hi>agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:50143:17"/>of Religion, though they ſhould not be of <hi>natural moral right</hi> (which yet many of them are) yet being commanded by him who is ſo wiſe and ſo good, to whom we have ſuch obligations lying upon us, and on whom we have ſuch an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute dependance we have, all the reaſon in the World to do them without murmuring or diſputing, and though the ſoveraignty of God is ſuch that he might juſtly try our obedience, and make us know our ſubjection to him, by requiring of us ſuch things as are meerly of <hi>poſitive right,</hi> yet it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident that in what he hath requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he hath not ſtood much upon his <hi>Soveraignty</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> but hath commanded ſuch things as he might juſtifie at an impartial Bar, though man were an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Creature, and co-ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate with him, and this will ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently appear by the enſuing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:50143:17"/>
               <head>SECT. III. <hi>The advantage which Men have by Religion in reſpect of their good name, honour being both a moral and a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural effect of vertue and holineſſe. The Hypocriſie of ſome that profeſſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, an argument of the excellency of it. Shame the preſent reward of ſin. None dare ſpeak againſt holineſs or holy men as ſuch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WHat I have hitherto ſaid hath been <hi>ab aequo,</hi> I ſhall now argue <hi>ab utili,</hi> and ſhew what advantages come to Mankind by a due obſervance of the <hi>Rules</hi> of the Goſpel, whereby the truth of the Apoſtles aſſertion will evidently appear, that <hi>Godlineſſe is profitable to all things,</hi> and is the chief inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>And firſt, let me conſider man in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:50143:18"/>his <hi>perſonal capacity,</hi> and his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral intereſts in ſuch a reſpect, and I will begin with that which is moſt <hi>extrinſick</hi> to him, <hi>viz.</hi> his <hi>good name</hi> which <hi>Solomon</hi> juſtly ſaith is <hi>rather to be choſen than great riches,</hi> and he adds a reaſon of it, <hi>loving favour is better than Silver or Gold.</hi> That is the effect of it, it commands a friendly reſpect from all, and ſo entertains him where ever he goes, is his <hi>harbinger</hi> to beſpeak him in all places an honourable reception, it is his <hi>ſurety,</hi> to vouch him in all his dealings with others, ſo that there is nothing can more ſweeten a Mans life to him, and indeed nothing which generous ſpirits do more eſteem. No greater incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to vertue among the Heathens than honour, and it is ordinarily ſeen that Men can more eaſily bear the loſſe of Goods than diſgrace or contempt, a breach in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, than a wound in their name. Now I will not here ſpeak of that honour, which after a few days ſhall be put upon all Godly men when they ſhall appear with Chriſt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:50143:18"/>in Glory, and ſhine like the Sun in the Kingdom of their Father, while others ſhall be cloathed with perpetual ſhame: Nor will I ſpeak of honour as it is a <hi>moral</hi> effect of Godlineſſe, God having promiſed <hi>to honour thoſe that honour him,</hi> and he that gave the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> favour in the eyes of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and <hi>made them to be pityed of them that carryed them away captive,</hi> can give a Man eſteem and repute among others.</p>
               <p>But I ſhall ſpeak chiefly of <hi>honour</hi> as it is a <hi>natural</hi> effect of Godlineſs, and it is worthy to be conſidered that that which at firſt view ſeems to reflect diſ-honourably upon Religion, and which many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove to the reproach of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of it, doth upon a ſerious weighing of the whole matter ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly commend it, and argue ſomething of more than ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry worth in it, and that is the <hi>Hypocriſie</hi> which is found among <hi>Chriſtians:</hi> this implies that there is ſomething in it which is attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive that men ſhould uſe ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:50143:19"/>to counterfeit it, and ſeek by a feigned ſhew of it to inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate themſelves into the eſteem of others whoſe good opinion they think moſt conſiderable. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, as I have already ſaid (and ſhall ſay again in due place) there are many ſcorn men for it, yet this is an evident proof that it is a thing of good report and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy; though we do not eſteem every thing that looks like Gold, becauſe it is ſometimes counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited, yet this is an argument of the worth of that which is Gold indeed: ſo, though 'tis true every one that makes profeſſion of God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe doth not preſently deſerve the honour and reſpect of a Godly Man, becauſe there are many Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites; yet it is an argument of the greater worth of ſuch as are Godly indeed. Pearls and Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds are oftener counterfeit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than thoſe things that are of mean value. What is there that begets an higher eſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men than that <hi>Humility, Meekneſs, Goodneſſe, Charity, Juſtice,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:50143:19"/>which the Goſpel requires, and which every true Chriſtian in ſome meaſure hath? It makes a Man (as was ſaid of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>) the <hi>Darling of Mankind,</hi> and makes his memory bleſſed. What is the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Character which you ſhall hear of ſuch a Man? He was a good Man, a quiet Man, you might have put your Life in his hand, his word was as good as his bond; and however the Devil cheats men with the hopes of eſteem in the World by a careleſſe neglect of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, though they gratifie the greateſt part of the World (in ſome reſpect) as they juſtifie their wicked wayes by their own pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; yet we ſhall obſerve (through the juſt judgment of God) <hi>ſhame</hi> is the <hi>preſent</hi> wages of ſin. <hi>Prov.</hi> 13.5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.21. and indeed the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> themſelves made <hi>honour</hi> the reward of <hi>vertue,</hi> ſo that a wicked Man according to them is not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of it. <hi>Pride</hi> is that which all abhor, <hi>ſwearing</hi> and <hi>blaſpheming</hi> are ſuch ſins as none gain by, and therefore will commend no man;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:50143:20"/>for, <hi>Drunkenneſſe</hi> diſcovers ſo much of a Mans weakneſſse, that it makes him obnoxious to every Mans pity or ſcorn; <hi>lying, injuſtice, oppreſſion,</hi> and other ſins againſt the <hi>ſecond table,</hi> being immediatly againſt our Neighbour, and ſo prejudicial to the intereſt of Mankind, cannot purchaſe any man any honour or eſteem; and though it is true, as I have before complained, that a Godly man is expoſed to ſcorn and reproach; yet, <hi>firſt,</hi> it is of ſuch whoſe reproaches we may glory in, and bind to us as a Crown. What was ſaid of <hi>Nero,</hi> is true of them, that it is likely to be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that is good which they ſpeak againſt; yea, commonly ſuch before they dye, juſtifie thoſe whom they reproached, and when they grow wiſer come to be of their mind, when they come to lye on their ſick beds, and to be convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by ſenſe and experience of what they would not believe, or at leaſt conſider before, that there is a <hi>vanity in every Creature, that they must dye, and that their former
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:50143:20"/>pleaſures will yield them no comfort at ſuch an hour:</hi> then they reproach themſelves more than formerly they reproached others, then they find that they were the fools for deſpiſing inſtruction, and wiſh now they were in the caſe of thoſe whom they deſpiſed; and which is yet more obſervable, Godlineſs doth command ſuch an eſteem from all, that none dare ſpeak againſt it, and you ſhall hardly hear any Godlyman reproached as ſuch as the <hi>Jews</hi> would not own that they ſtoned Chriſt for a <hi>good work,</hi> but for <hi>Blaſphemy;</hi> when Wicked Men reproach others, they will not by any means acknowledge that it is for <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> but for <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngodlineſſe,</hi> for Hypocriſie, for being too nice and ſuperſtitious, doing more than God requires, for Covetouſneſſe, or ſuch like ſins; ſo that by their own confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſincerity, obſerving what God hath commanded, charity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are good and commendable, and ſo they are condemned out of their own mouths. Let ſin ſeek excuſes
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:50143:21"/>and ſubterfuges. <hi>Vertue (as truth) ſeeks no corners, knows no ſhame.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <head>SECT. IV. <hi>How much Godlineſſe condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth to the preſerving and increaſe of Mens Eſtates, which Sin doth like a Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, waſt and conſume. An illuſtration of</hi> Jer. 17.11. <hi>and</hi> Hoſ. 9.11. <hi>Objections anſwered, which Men make from that Juſtice and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity which Religion obliges Men to, and from thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſes and loſſes which it expoſes them to, as alſo from experience and daily obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe next intereſt of Man in his perſonal capacity which I ſhall conſider, is the furniture of this life for bearing his charges in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:50143:21"/>his Pilgrimage while he is on his way towards his long home, and though <hi>Riches</hi> (by reaſon of the abuſe of them) ſometimes ſeem to be undervalued both by God and Man, in the Scripture and other writings, yet in themſelves they are uſeful and deſirable, and if we ſhould underſtand theſe things <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely</hi> and <hi>ſimply,</hi> which are ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of them, not in a <hi>certain re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> and <hi>ſecundum quid</hi> (as they ſpeak) it might rather be ſaid, the curſe of the Lord makes rich than his bleſſing; thereby a Man is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of doing good to others, and our Saviour hath pronounced it more bleſſed to give than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, he is able to command his own affairs, he is freed from the temptations of poverty to a ſinful flattery and pleaſing of Men, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croaching upon Gods time or Mens Eſtates, from diſtracting cares a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the neceſſaries of this life, they are a defence to him, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his own conceit, but really lifting him up, that the foot of contempt may not trample upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:50143:22"/>him, and that whatever is praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy in him may be more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuous to others which is little taken notice of in the poor, whoſe wiſdom, yea, all other graces and vertues are deſpiſed. Now as <hi>the race is not to the ſwift, nor the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel to the ſtrong,</hi> ſo neither are Riches alwayes to the diligent, or induſtrious, or wiſe, but to thoſe whom God favours with his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. <hi>Godlineſſe hath the promiſe both of this life, and that to come,</hi> though God hath not abſolutely promiſed abundance or ſuperflui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, neceſſaries he hath; ſo that though <hi>the Lions</hi> (whereby we may according to the language of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, underſtand thoſe who have both cruelty and power to oppreſſe others) <hi>may lack and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer hunger, thoſe that fear the Lord ſhall want no good thing.</hi> Again, Godlineſſe may be ranked a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>natural</hi> cauſes as well as amongſt the <hi>moral</hi> cauſes of <hi>riches.</hi> Do but conſider what diligence the Goſpel requires in our parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular callings, and though (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:50143:22"/>to what I lately ſaid) this is not the only or ſolitary cauſe of <hi>Riches,</hi> yet it is a means which God doth ordinarily bleſſe. Do but further conſider what ſobriety and moderation is required in Meat, Drink, Apparel, and we ſhall eaſily conceive how much it doth tend to the increaſe of Mens ſubſtance, and ſtopping up thoſe chinks and crannies, at which other Mens E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates do run out. On the other hand we ſhall find many ſins both <hi>moral</hi> and <hi>natural</hi> cauſes of decays in mens Eſtates, it is true all ſin doth make men obnoxious to the curſe: but there are many ſins which derive a curſe upon Men, which in a ſpecial manner (like the ruſt) devours their Riches; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly <hi>oppreſſion</hi> and <hi>injuſtice,</hi> the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet Jer.</hi> 17.11. elegantly ſhews how the deſigns of Men, for ſetting up themſelves thereby prove abortive, <hi>as the Partridge ſitteth upon eggs and hatcheth them not, ſo he that getteth Riches and not by right, ſhall leave them in the midſt of his dayes, and in the end ſhall be a fool.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:50143:23"/>Some Birds Men take care of to ſecure them againſt injuries and violence as thoſe that are tame, others there are whoſe uſeleſſeneſs makes them neglected of all and ſo is their ſecurity, others there are able to reſiſt the violence of the Birds of prey; the Partridge is none of theſe, and ſo is moſt likely of all others to miſcarry and prove a prey to violence: ſo the unjuſt Oppreſſor may indeed gather Riches, but he ſhall ſoon leave them, <hi>himſelf</hi> is like the <hi>Graſſe,</hi> but his <hi>Glory</hi> is like the <hi>Flower</hi> of the Graſs (which oft falls off while the ſtalk ſtands) and he ſhall out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live his Glory, ſome Mens Glory flies away from the <hi>conception,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from the <hi>womb,</hi> others from the <hi>birth, Hoſ.</hi> 9.11. ſome mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns fail while they are projecting and contriving them, others while they are travelling with them, or labouring to effect them, <hi>they fade in their wayes,</hi> others when they have juſt attained them, and arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at their end, as the Rich Man, but when he ſhould ſolace himſelf
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:50143:23"/>in the enjoyment of them, they ſhall be taken away like the Corn, and the wine in the Harveſt or vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, and in his end he ſhall be a fool, that is according to the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of the Scripture (wherein words of exiſtence are put ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times only for appearance and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation) he ſhall appear to be a fool, though formerly he ſeemed to be of the wiſe of the World, that knew how to get moſt for himſelf in the ſcuffle of the World, wherein almoſt every one ſcram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles to get as much as he can to himſelf to make his own heap big<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt, but increaſing that <hi>which is not his own, Hab.</hi> 2.6. but of right belongs to others, he proves like the Dog in the fable, that not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with what he had, but catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at more loſt all. So Adultery (through the curſe of God) is a devouring Fire that conſumes and waſts a Mans ſubſtance. So the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous unmerciful Man unfolds that riddle. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.24. he <hi>ſcatters by gathering</hi> whiles he retains his Riches when God requires them
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:50143:24"/>for the relief of the poor, or by his extortion and oppreſſion ſqueezeth out the ſweat, yea, it may be the blood of the poor: what is ſo either gotten or kept proves a canker to his Eſtate to devour it. Yea, there are many ſins, which are the natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral cauſes of poverty, and if God ſhould leave men only to the genu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine natural effects of their ſin, they would ſoon <hi>fade in their wayes,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.11. <hi>By means of a whoriſh Woman a Man is brought to a morſel of Bread,</hi> her words are ſo enſnaring, he is loſt that is once entangled with them, and it is a ſad ſign ſuch a one is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandoned of God. So the unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful Man and the Oppreſſor ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth himſelf to the curſes of the poor, yea, to their rage and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence if ever they have the oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of a popular tumult. So how doth Pride (like ruſt) eat up Mens Silver and God. <hi>Drowſineſs cloaths a Man with rags,</hi> ſo Glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony and Drunkenneſſe feed upon Mens Eſtates till they have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured them. Envy and malice
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:50143:24"/>beget contentions and quarrels which caſt Men into chargeable Law-ſuits. If Men would in their Books of Accounts allow ſome pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges for their Luſts, and ſet down what they ſpend on them more than what <hi>Nature, Reaſon, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> require, and write ſo much laid out at ſuch a time for <hi>Pride,</hi> ſo much at another time for <hi>Pleaſure</hi> and Voluptuouſneſſe, ſo much for <hi>envy</hi> in a Law-ſuit to vex ſuch a one, ſo much for entertainments, Buildings, Gardens, Feſtivals, Pomp of Funerals, (I ſpeak not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a <hi>decorum</hi> and moderation in ſuch things anſwerable to a Mans rank and Eſtate, but only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſuperfluity and exceſſe in theſe things, which Mens own Conſciences will tell them, ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and vain glory put them upon) let them ſet down ſo much <hi>lucrum ceſſans</hi> from idleneſſe and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence in their particular callings, and they ſhall find ſuch a retinue of Luſts (which Religion would make them ſhake off and aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don) as chargeable as a train of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:50143:25"/>Servants, though the old com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint ſhould be true. <hi>Quot ſervi, tot Fures.</hi> Notwithſtanding all that I have ſaid, many have ſuch a prejudice againſt Religion, that they think if a Man begin ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to addict himſelf thereto, it ſoon ſpoils his thriving in the World. As <hi>firſt,</hi> it is obſerved by many that it takes up much of Mens time, and many as ſoon as they begin to be ſo ſtrict in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, neglect their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular callings. To this I anſwer, God is but little beholding to men that complain that his ſervice takes up too much of their time, there are none in the World amongſt the devout orders that conſecrate their time more entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to God than thouſands do to the Devil and to their own luſts; yea, how few are there that do not allow more time to Pride in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorning themſelves? to pleaſure in vain ſports and recreations? to idle diſcourſe? to fruitleſſe viſits? to ſuperfluous ſleep &amp; eaſe than God requires to be ſpent ſolely in his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:50143:25"/>ſervice? he allows us time enough for our private affairs and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar callings. God is not ſerved only in prayer and reading, and hearing his word, but in the works of our ordinary callings. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.13. What is there ſaid of ſervants is true of others alſo in their ſeveral ſtations, while they duely attend their lawful vocations. It is true, ſome Chriſtians may not have pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to ſhare their time equally betwixt their <hi>general</hi> and <hi>particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi> callings, but ſuch are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily obſerved to be young Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, (as they are called) that is, ſuch as have had but late acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the power and practice of Godlineſſe, and ſomething is to be indulged to theſe who at firſt converſion many times find ſo much delight and ſweetneſſe in exerciſes of Religion, that they know not how to leave them off. We know under the Law he that had marryed a Wife was diſpenſed with the firſt year to ſtay at home and ſolace himſelf with her and not forced to go out to War. Some
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:50143:26"/>again are ready to complain of the charge of Charity which Religion doth oblige a Man to. To ſuch I anſwer, nature it ſelf doth bind a Man to the ſame charity, that Chriſtianity binds him to, only Chriſtianity directing us to right principles and ends in ſuch actions, makes them turn to our good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. So that <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> is the beſt <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> God gives us bond for repayment. <hi>Prov.</hi> 19.17. and he is a good pay-maſter. If a Man would lay up ſomewhat againſt an evil day, he cannot put it into bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hands. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.2. If the worſt come, and the hand of vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence ſhould ſeize on his Eſtate, yet he may ſay with him in <hi>Seneca, I have that ſtill which I have given a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> yea, a Man of meer humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and generoſity, cannot but have ſuch a ſympathy with others in their ſufferings, that in relieving them, he relieves himſelf, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> when <hi>Darius</hi> ſent a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement to him by his Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors for his civility to his Wife, Mother, Daughters, whom he had
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:50143:26"/>taken Captives, returned him an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that <hi>it was in vain to comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with an Enemy, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour he had ſhewed to them was not ſo much out of affection to him, as to ſatisfie his own nature, which could not inſult over the miſery of others.</hi> For the charge of the ſervice of God, let ſhame for ever cloath them, and confuſion cover them as a Garment that complain of it. Let an Heathen, an <hi>Alexander</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn them, who when <hi>Leonidas</hi> reproved him for ſpending ſo much incenſe in ſacrifice to his Gods, and told him he might do that when he had taken the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries from whence it came, having taken them, ſent him incenſe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance, and ſent him word, that <hi>for the future he ſhould not be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in his offerings to his Gods, for he had found by experience that what was offered to them they paid with <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</hi> And further, our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence now under the Goſpel about the ſervice of God, is nothing to what it was formerly under the Law. What I ſaid before in reſpect
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:50143:27"/>of time, I may ſay here in reſpect of Eſtate, what Men ſpend upon Religious uſes and works of chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, is not comparable to what Men ſpend upon their Luſts. And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever call themſelves Chriſtians ſhould diſdain that any ſhould be more free in the ſervice of the Devil, than they are in the ſervice of Chriſt. Neither is it Chriſtian charity but blind zeal and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition that makes men give away their Eſtates (as is ordinary a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Papiſts) to maintain others in eaſe and idleneſſe under a pretence of devoting themſelves to religious exerciſes, and the imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of I know not what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Saints. Others are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to complain of that juſtice and equity, that Religion doth ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige a man to obſerve in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce with others, as hindering their thriving in the World: but I have ſaid enough already of the curſe that follows injuſtice and oppreſſion, to ſhew how vain this objection is, beſides the puniſhment inflicted by Man for theſe ſins,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:50143:27"/>which are the more odious to Men becauſe they are againſt our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor immediately (as many other ſins are not) ſo as men are more ſenſible of them, and as much as they can avoid having any thing to do with ſuch as are falſe and unjuſt in their dealings with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Some object further the ſufferings which Religion expoſeth a Man oftentimes to. But to this I may anſwer, as to the former, Men ordinarily ſuffer more for ſin. The <hi>Devil</hi> hath had more <hi>Martyrs</hi> than <hi>Chriſt</hi> in moſt Ages of the World; that is, more have ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for doing the Devils works, and fulfilling his Luſts, than for the ſervice of Chriſt. How many are there that ſuffer impriſonment, baniſhment, loſſe of goods, yea, of life for injuſtice, oppreſſion, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, adultery, ſedition, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſins. And I have oft thought it might be a great comfort to one impriſoned for the cauſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, for Chriſts ſake, to think he might have ſuffered the ſame for his <hi>ſin,</hi> if he had been left to his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:50143:28"/>Luſts as others; or for his <hi>miſery,</hi> for Debt and Poverty, whereas now he ſuffers the ordinary lot of Mankind, in ſuch a cauſe, on ſuch an occaſion, as it ſhall prove his greateſt advantage, God reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo bountifully, whatever a Man undergoes for his ſake, both with preſent ſpiritual comforts, and future everlaſting Glory. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, experience may be objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all that I have ſaid, it being obſerved that the followers of Chriſt have the leaſt ſhare ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily in the things of the World.</p>
               <p>But I anſwer to this, it is not becauſe Religion is any way pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicial to Mens worldly Eſtates, but becauſe God in his free and wiſe Providence doth for the moſt part chooſe the poor of the World to be the Heirs of his Kingdom, both that he may confound the wiſdom of Men, and ſtain the Pride of their glory, chooſing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Mans ordinary judgment and choice, and alſo becauſe out of his bounty he is pleaſed to give many a portion in <hi>this Life,</hi> to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:50143:28"/>whom he intends none hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Further, however God doth not many times give his Children ſuperfluities, he ordinarily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides for their neceſſities, and many may make <hi>Davids</hi> obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>that they have not ſeen the righteous forſaken, nor his ſeed beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging their bread.</hi> Yea, I may add, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 37.16. <hi>A little that a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Man hath, is better than great Treaſures of many wicked,</hi> becauſe he is ſatisfied with what he hath.</p>
               <p>The vanity of the Creature proceeds from the vanity of Mens minds, when Men will make the Creature their chief happineſſe, they muſt needs find it vanity and vexation of ſpirit, becauſe it doth not anſwer their expactati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from it, they looking for more from it than ever God put in it. But a Godly Man having ſomething elſe for his chief good, which is ſufficient to fill his moſt enlarged deſires, and to anſwer the higheſt expectations that he can have from it, he makes uſe of the Creature only for the end,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:50143:29"/>to which God hath appointed it, to ſupply his bodily neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to be a <hi>Viatioum</hi> in this his Pilgrimage towards Heaven, which end it is ſufficient to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, ſo that there is none can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce and take pleaſure in the Creature more than a Godly Man.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:50143:29"/>
               <head>SECT. V. <hi>The influence which Religion hath even upon our bodies, how far it conduceth to our health. Diſeaſes of the body ordinarily proceed from the diſtempers of the Soul. That Temperance, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence in our callings and moderation of our paſſions, which the Goſpel requires and teaches, is the beſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE next intereſt of Man, which I ſhall ſpeak of, doth yet more nearly concern him, and that is <hi>Health,</hi> which is not only as one calls it the <hi>Paradiſe of all ſenſual pleaſures;</hi> wherein they grow and flouriſh, but the <hi>Salt</hi> that ſeaſons all our worldly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, without which we can find very little ſayour in them, yea, are not only incapable of enjoying
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:50143:30"/>all other things, but of enjoying our ſelves, yea, the want of it makes us as unable to do good as to enjoy good, but only as we may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples of Faith and Patience to others. Now though Religion chiefly concerns the Soul, and ſeems to have little influence on Mens bodies, yet I will confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirm (what may ſeem a <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox</hi> to many) that the precepts of Chriſt well obſerved would free as many from Diſeaſes as his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles, they would prevent as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes as his miracles cured. How many are there whoſe bodies are filled with the ſins of their ſouls, which they have tired and worn out in the ſervice of their inſatiable Luſts, which are like fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Riders, that tire out their Beaſts they ride on before they be tired themſelves. Though Men are not preſently ſenſible of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayes in their health by riot, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, and ſuch like ſins, they lay in daily the ſeeds of thoſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes which many groan under in their old age, though others feel
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:50143:30"/>them ſooner. We ordinarily ſay that <hi>exceſſe</hi> kills more than the <hi>Sword.</hi> By exceſſe we are not to underſtand only eating and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſurfeiting and drunkenneſs, or till nature be ſo oppreſſed that it diſchargeth it ſelf of its burden, but when Men make their appetite not their reaſon, the meaſure of their allowance. It would require the skil of a Phyſician to enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Diſeaſes which are the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Mens ſins, but every one may eaſily obſerve that the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Rules which the beſt Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans preſcribe for the preſervation of <hi>Health,</hi> require nothing more than <hi>Temperance</hi> and <hi>exerciſe,</hi> the former Religion ſtrictly injoyns, and though it do not require the later as ſuch, or under ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yet in effect it requires it of moſt, commanding diligence in Mens callings, and condemning idleneſſe, which is the ſource of ſo many diſeaſes, as daily experience will evince, it being obvious to the obſervation of all, that <hi>Health</hi> is the poor Mans priviledge, and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:50143:31"/>moſt common among the Rich, who live in idleneſſe, though they have many other advantages above the poor for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their health, beſides thoſe two cauſes of ſickneſſe there is a third, which religion doth remove, or at leaſt much correct, and that is, inordinate paſſions, ſuch as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Fear, Sorrow, Envy,</hi> which have a very malignant influence upon the Body, and there is ſcarce any thing which tends ſo much to the poizing and ballancing of the humors of the body, (which is ſo neceſſary for the preſervation of the health) as a well compoſed temper of mind, and calmneſſe, and quietneſs in the Soul, which Religion doth not only teach, but (which is more) doth in a great meaſure effect, and therein ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds the <hi>morals</hi> of <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> as we ſhall in due place more fully ſee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:50143:31"/>
               <head>SECT. VI. <hi>Religion forbids us not any pleaſures which are agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to nature, reaſon, or Mans own intereſt. None can more freely enjoy plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures than a Godly Man.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is yet another thing which many account their great intereſt (and their great pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice againſt Religion is, that they conceive it inconſiſtent therewith) and that is <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> Now if we take <hi>Pleaſure</hi> in a large ſence as it is taken in Scripture, that inward Joy, Comfort and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction which accompanies an holy Life, and thoſe <hi>everlaſting pleaſures</hi> at Gods right hand, which a holy Life leads to, will fall after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards under conſideration. And as for thoſe <hi>bodily pleaſures,</hi> which in this place are chiefly intended, Religion doth not at all forbid them, nor deprive a Man of them;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:50143:32"/>and it is an unjuſt calumny of ſome that God hath put inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons into mans nature to ſuch things as he hath forbidden him, and that this is the chief cauſe of ſo much ſin in the World: But theſe men know not what ſpirit they are of. It was the ſuggeſtion of the Devil to Man in Paradiſe, that God (as if he envyed mans happineſſe) had laid a reſtraint on them to keep them from that which (as the Devil would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them) he knew might bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their condition, and advance them to an equality with himſelf, as if it had been a ſmall matter that he had allowed them ſuch li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to enjoy all the pleaſures of Paradiſe, and to eat of all the fruit of it, ſave only that in the midſt of the Garden. But they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived a juſt recompence for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving the Devil rather than God. It is the ſame ſpirit which now perſwades Men that God hath dealt hardly with us, to interdict us the enjoyment of that wherein we might find ſuch pleaſure and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:50143:32"/>ſatisfaction, whereas he hath ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manifeſted his goodneſſe to Man, in that he hath put into him ſuch inclinations, as he may take pleaſure in thoſe things which are neceſſary for the <hi>propagation</hi> of the <hi>ſpecies,</hi> or for the <hi>conſervation</hi> of the <hi>individuals</hi> of Mankind; and he doth not forbid our pleaſure in theſe, but only forbids <hi>Gluttony</hi> and <hi>Drunkenneſſe,</hi> which is exceſs in the uſe of meats and drinks, and <hi>Adultery,</hi> which is the miſplacing of theſe deſires which he hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for the ſatisfaction of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind without ſin: and we have no cauſe to complain of Gods bound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of us in theſe things, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wonder that there ſhould be any need of any Laws to forbid ſuch irregularities therein, as we ſhould wonder that any ſhould make Laws ſtrictly to forbid Men to burn their own houſes, to cut their own fleſh, to drink poyſon, if we conſider the miſchiefs that enſue upon our exceeding the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits which God hath yet ſet us in theſe things, in impairing our
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:50143:33"/>Health, waſting our Eſtates, ſtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our honour, breeding diſcords in Families, depriving us of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and turning us into Bruits, expoſing us ſometimes to Mans rage, ſometimes to the penalty of human Laws. In ſhort, God hath not only provided for the ſupply of our neceſſities, but for our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and comfort. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.15. 2ly. Religion allows a Man to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy and take comfort in theſe things which God hath given us. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.24, 25, 26.5.18.9.7, 8, 9. Yea, requires we ſhould rejoyce in them. <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.7.12.18. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.26. <hi>cap.</hi> 16.11, 14. <hi>cap.</hi> 26.11. 3ly. There is none can take more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in theſe things than a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 2.25. <hi>Solomon</hi> might haſten as much as any to ſuch plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, not ſo much as he was a <hi>King,</hi> and had all things in abundance: but as he was a <hi>good Man,</hi> and in the favour of God. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.7. But this I have elſewhere touched. Sect. 4. and ſect. 8. If any account it hard to be reſtrained from <hi>unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral pleaſures,</hi> I may ſay as <hi>Joaſh</hi> of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:50143:33"/>
                  <hi>Baal, Judges</hi> 6.31. <hi>Will you plead for</hi> theſe? <hi>He that will plead for</hi> theſe, <hi>let him preſently be put to Death.</hi> He that cannot content himſelf with <hi>moderate pleaſures,</hi> without exceſſe, let him go and learn of Bruit-beaſts, that will not eat and drink to Gluttony and Drunkenneſſe. He that cannot ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie himſelf unleſs he may wholly proſtitute himſelf to pleaſure, and ſpend his whole time therein, as if he were put into the World, as the <hi>Leviathan</hi> into the Sea, <hi>to play there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in: Pſal.</hi> 104.26. Let them learn of a <hi>Heathen,</hi> who would ſay, <hi>He is not worthy the name of a Man, thàt would ſpend a whole day in pleaſure.</hi> So that Religion reſtrains us no more in the uſe of <hi>Pleaſures</hi> than <hi>nature, reaſon,</hi> or our own intereſt reſtrains us, but rather teacheth us how we may enjoy them more pure and refined, without any ſting of <hi>guilt,</hi> or check of Conſcience, which may allay the ſweetneſſe of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:50143:34"/>
               <head>SECT. VII. <hi>The advantage which we have by Religion in reſpect of our Souls. Firſt, in being thereby reſtored to the image of God, and that ſpiritual beauty which hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced by ſin.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Now come yet nearer to our ſelves, to that Divine part whereby we hold intelligence with the upper World, have our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation in Heaven, with God and Angels, to theſe our bodies are but as a box, a caſe to a precious Jewel, and the advantages which I have hitherto ſpoken of are not worthy to be compared with theſe that Godlineſſe brings to the Soul. And I will firſt ſpeak of what a Godly Man hath thereby in <hi>enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> and <hi>poſſeſſion,</hi> then of what he hath in <hi>hopes</hi> and <hi>reverſion,</hi> and I will begin with the reſtorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of man to the condition from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:50143:34"/>which he fell, or the <hi>renewing of the image of God</hi> in him. To have ſeen that great Monarch. <hi>Dan.</hi> 4. in the greateſt Glory, priding himſelf in his Majeſty, and after to have ſeen him not only deveſted of his Glory, degraded from his dignity, but deprived of his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and putting on the manners of Beaſts of the Field, and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing amongſt them, would have moved a Mans compaſſion; though he, it is likely was no more ſenſible of his own unhappineſſe, (being bereaved of humanity) than thoſe in the fable, that being by the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantments of <hi>Circe</hi> turned into Beaſts, diſdained the offer of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi> to have them reſtored to their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſhape, being debaſed in their ſouls, as well as metamorphoſed in their bodies, and ſo not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the felicity of the ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; but ſuch were the more to be pityed, by how much the leſſe they could pity themſelves. This is the condition of Mankind. We are all of a good houſe, well deſcended, of a noble ſtock and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:50143:35"/>Original: but are fallen into decay, have loſt the luſtre of that Family from which we came, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the off-ſpring of God) and we are become <hi>like the Beaſts which periſh, Pſal.</hi> 49.21. So ſome under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that place, Man being in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor continued not, ſoon fell from his Eſtate of dignity and happineſs, and became bruitiſh in his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and affections. Satan, that old Magician, by his enchantments hath bewitched us from that form wherein we were at firſt created, into the form of <hi>Beaſts;</hi> ſo that Men are become <hi>Lions</hi> for rage, cruelty, oppreſſion; <hi>Foxes</hi> for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty in evil; <hi>Swine</hi> for ſilthineſſe and uncleanneſs; <hi>Dogs</hi> for envy and malice; <hi>Wolves</hi> for rapine; yea, as the <hi>wild Aſſes Colt</hi> for folly and ſtupidity: the Scripture accounts it neither incivility nor calumny to deſcribe Men by ſuch compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. Now it is only true God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and that regeneration, (which miſerable Man doth as little underſtand, and much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe, as thoſe even now mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:50143:35"/>did the offer of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lyſſes</hi>) which muſt reſtore us to our former ſtate. The Goſpel (as a ſpiritual charm) brings us to that ſhape and form which our firſt Parents loſt. And though poor ignorant Men nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther underſtand their own defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity, nor that beauty of holineſſe which adorns the ſouls of thoſe who are renewed, according to the Image of God, (as the Jews deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Chriſt, and eſteemed him not, as ſeeing no form nor comlineſs in him, though he was to thoſe who had a ſpiritual diſcerning, and an eye of Faith to ſee that Divine excellency and perfection that was in him, the chiefeſt of ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, and altogether lovely) yet there is an inward beauty of the Soul, obvious only to the eyes of God that regards the hidden Man of the heart, and thoſe who have a ſpiritual diſcerning to diſcern ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual things, which (as the beauty of the outward man conſiſts in <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, proportion,</hi> and <hi>perfection of parts</hi>) ſtands in a due regard of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faculty and affection of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:50143:36"/>ſoul to its proper object, and a juſt ſubordination to each other, the ſuperior irradiated by a Divine light to judge of every thing as the matter requires, and accordingly to command the inferior, which by an obſequious ſubjection yields to the authority, and executes the commands of the ſuperior, (and is not like a bone out of a joynt, which is not ſubject to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the locomotive faculty) and the whole tinctured with a Divine holineſs, juſtice and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. It would be a ſad ſpectacle to behold a Man bowed together, that he could not look up, his eyes cloſed up with filthy putrid mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, his lips black, and ſwelled as if they were poyſoned, his breath ſtinking, to the offence of all that come near him, Lame of his feet, that he could not go, his bowels hanging out. In a word, from <hi>head to foot full of bruiſes and putrifying ſores,</hi> thus is man by nature to the eyes of God, bowed down to the earth, minding earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things, his underſtanding dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:50143:36"/>and the eyes thereof cloſed by vile and corrupt affections, his lips breaking out with filthy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as if the poyſon of Aſps were under them, his throat like an open Sepulchre, ſending forth ſuch unſavory diſcourſe as is offenſive to pure ears, that knows not how to tread a right ſtep in the way of Gods commandments, void of the bowels of pity and compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the plague of his heart, (his natural in-bred corruption) breaking forth daily into ſinful actions which are as ſo many botches and ſores to render a Man loathſom in the ſight of God, to whom our inward Man is as naked and open as our outward Man to eyes of fleſh. A form of Godlineſs and the paint or varniſh of an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward profeſſion, may help to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal ſome of this deformity from the eyes of Man, but it is only that <hi>Fountain ſet open to the houſe of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem <hi>to waſh in for ſin, and for un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneſs,</hi> that will reſtore to Man his primitive ſoundneſs and beauty,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:50143:37"/>as <hi>Naamans</hi> fleſh by waſhing in <hi>Jordan</hi> was reſtored as the fleſh of a young Child. This is the imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate effect of Regeneration, and though the work is not perſected at once as to degrees, yet it will be <hi>as the light that ſhines clearer and clearer till the perfect day, we being transformed daily more and more into the Image of God, from Glory to Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by his Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:50143:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>Tranquility of mind the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Godly Man. A due ordering of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, not a ſtoical Apa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy neceſſary thereto. Peace of Conſcience unknown to the Heathen Philoſophers, and attainable only by true Religion. Objectionsground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the moroſeneſs, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward troubles of Chriſtians anſwered.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE next advantage of the Soul, in this World by Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, is <hi>Tranquility of Mind,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Man is exempted from the importunity of inordinate paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and from the ſecret (though ſevere) laſhes of an accuſing terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Conſcience, which wound deeper than Scorpions. This the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> cry up as the ſum of a happy life; but what is ſaid of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:50143:38"/>happineſſe in general, I may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply to this part of it: <hi>Philoſophy</hi> ſeeks it, <hi>Theology</hi> ſinds it, but <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> poſſeſſeth it. As <hi>Paul</hi> told the <hi>Athenians;</hi> he <hi>declared unto them, him whom they ignorantly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped.</hi> So the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> diſcovers that which the <hi>Heathen Moraliſt</hi> blindly purſues, but it is only the <hi>Godly Man</hi> who hath his Soul throughly tinctured with true Grace that enjoyes this tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and hereby I mean a ſedate calmneſſe of affections, whereby a man is freed from the terrors of an accuſing Conſcience, and from the <hi>impetus</hi> and violence of unruly paſſions, which make him as <hi>the troubled Sea caſting up continually mire and dirt,</hi> diſcovering in the effects of ſuch vile affections the filthineſſe that lies deep in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom of their hearts, ſo <hi>foaming out their own ſhame,</hi> theſe luſts (like the Devil in the poor man that caſt him ſometimes into the fire, and ſometimes into the water, or made him cut himſelf with ſtones) hurry men with violence, ſometime into
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:50143:38"/>one extream, ſometimes into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and make them <hi>pierce them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves through with many ſorrows,</hi> and make dreadful wounds and gaſhes in their own Conſciences, ruſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them into a thouſand dangers, as the unruly horſe doth the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der into the battel. But I have already ſaid enough of the diſeaſes, quarrels, and other inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that mens ſins ſubject them to, which are but the fulfilling of theſe importunate Luſts which will never let a man reſt, but are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſolliciting for ſatisfaction, and can never be ſatisfied, but en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>large themſelves continually, as Hell; and thoſe fleſhly Luſts do not only war <hi>againſt</hi> the Soul, but <hi>in</hi> the Soul againſt one another: this is our unhappineſs that we muſt ſerve <hi>divers</hi> Luſts, ſo that a man is not only (as one compares him) like a Servant in an Inne, where there are many Gueſts, ſome cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with importunity one way, ſome another, ſome up ſtairs, ſome down, but like thoſe that live on the Frontiers of a Kingdom, bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:50143:39"/>upon the Territories of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother Prince, or betwixt two Garriſons in a civil War, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice is required of both, he knows not whom to obey, both require more taxes than he knows how to pay; thus is miſerable man tortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, while he is a ſlave to his Luſts, one calls one way, another calls a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother way, <hi>Pride</hi> puts him upon one thing, <hi>Covetouſneſſe</hi> counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, <hi>Senſuality</hi> calls him ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way, <hi>Pride</hi> reclaims and tells him it will ſtain his reputation, ſpot his honour. Now for free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man from this baſeſt ſlavery, the Goſpel is much more effectual than all the precepts of morality, as it more clearly layes before us the expreſſe commands, and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory will and pleaſure of the Soveraign Law-giver, as it infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth theſe with promiſes and threatnings, of ſuch things as there is either a deep ſilence of amongſt the Philoſophers, or which at leaſt they deſcry but at a great diſtance, and ſeem to make ſome imperfect diſcovery of which the Goſpel
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:50143:39"/>doth evidently demonſtrate. And which is more than all this, there doth a ſpirit of Life and Power accompany the Goſpel where it is received, which changeth the Soul into another form; there is a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine nature thereby communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whereby men become as it were new Creatures, have new thoughts, and new affections, whereby they now ſavour the things of the ſpirit, as they did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the things of the fleſh. The Old Man is mortified by the ſpirit; that, as in old age <hi>deſire fails,</hi> (as we have a proof in <hi>Barzillai</hi> that taſted not the ſweetneſſe of the Creatures, as formerly) ſo when a Mans Luſts are mortified, he hath not a deſire after forbidden vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and the pleaſures of ſin as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. <hi>Philoſophy</hi> indeed hath one <hi>Polemo</hi> to boaſt of, but the Goſpel thouſands whoſe natures have been ſo changed by its power, that they have become quite other perſons, and whatever Morality can furniſh us with to perſwade, the Goſpel hath the ſame in greater evidence,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:50143:40"/>and much more: beſides, a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an may more truly ſay of the Goſpel, than one ſaid of Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, <hi>he thereby learns to want what others enjoy,</hi> not that any man hath more pleaſure, or finds more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentin what he poſſeſſeth, than the Chriſtian, that hath all ſweetened to him by the favour of God, and knows that it is not his only por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to others when they dye, <hi>wo to you, ye have received your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation;</hi> but he doth not diſquiet himſelf with the deſire of more than God hath given him, and it is better to be content with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, than to have much, and not to be ſatisfied, better to enjoy perfect health, and eat and drink no more than nature requires, than to be troubled with the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petitus caninus,</hi> and be continually eating, or a <hi>Dropſie,</hi> and be always drinking. So for thoſe natural e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils which are the objects of our fear and ſorrow, as they are future and foreſeen, or preſent and ſelt, the Chriſtian hath the advantage
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:50143:40"/>of all others for bearing them, not only as <hi>Hope, Patience, Meekneſſe</hi> are the fruits of the ſpirit which he works by that ſpecial power and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergy which he puts forth in Gods choſen ones; but as the Goſpel doth furniſh him with moral argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, much more effectual to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade to patience, than any that are learned in the Schools of the Philoſophers, as <hi>it is in vain to be troubled at what we cannot help: all good hath a mixture of evil, and all evil hath a mixture of good. There is a viciſſitudo of fortunes, ſo that in adverſity a Man may hope that proſperity will ſucceed. We ſhould conſider the condition of others who ſuffer the like things with our ſelves. Bearing afflictions, will harden us to undergo them better,</hi> (as Iron grows harder by being oft heated in the fire,) <hi>ſometimes injuries prove ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious to thoſe who ſuffer them.</hi> Theſe and ſuch like rational con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations may help to correct the exceſſe of Mens paſſions, but it is only the Goſpel which diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers the care and ſingular love of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:50143:41"/>God to his people in all the eviſs that befall them, he being with them, ſympathizing with them, (ſo far as is conſiſtent with his happineſſe and perfection) order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all things by his wiſe and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful Providence, ſitting as a refi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, while he caſts his Gold and Silver into the Furnace to purifie it, ordering all things for the good of his choſen: this may make us not only patient in tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, but <hi>to glory</hi> in it, not only to conquer in our ſufferings, but to be <hi>more then Conquerors.</hi> Indeed all that aſſume to themſelves the title of Chriſtians, enjoy not this <hi>tranquility,</hi> for many arrogate this to themſelves which belongs not to them, thoſe that are Chriſtians indeed, attain to this but by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, none are abſolutely perfect in this life, and perfect peace of mind is not an abſolute freedom from all paſſion, not an <hi>apathy,</hi> but <hi>tranquillitas ordinis,</hi> when every af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection keeps its own place, and doth its proper work. When <hi>Fear</hi> is the <hi>Souls Gentinel</hi> to warn it of
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:50143:41"/>approaching danger, that being forewarned, it may before-armed, when <hi>Sorrow</hi> is the <hi>temper</hi> of the Soul, or the ballaſt of it to keep it ſteady, <hi>Angercos Fortit udinis &amp; ingenii,</hi> the mettle of it to fit it for action, and the <hi>Oyl of Gladneſſe,</hi> making the face to ſhine, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as marrow to the bones, making our converſation more acceptable and agreeable unto others, our life more pleaſing and comfortable to our ſelves. But that wherein a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian hath the greateſt advantage is <hi>Peace of Conſcience,</hi> the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſollicitations of Satan and our own Luſts, to the commiſſion of ſin are not ſo diſquieting to the Soul, as the rebukes and clamors of Conſcience after the commiſſion of it. The Devil is a meer <hi>Trapan,</hi> that draws Men into a Plot againſt Heaven, and when he hath enſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, is the firſt that accuſeth them, ſollicites men importunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſin by the ſtrongeſt entice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, afterwards affrights their Conſciences by aggravating their guilt to them, and this is a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupation
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:50143:42"/>of Hell,</hi> as peace of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the firſt fruits and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eaven. As <hi>Vertue is its own</hi> reward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſin is its own puniſhment; guilt followes ſin, as the ſhaddow doth the body, haunting the ſinner like a hideous Ghoſt, and continually terrifying him. It is true, many do not feel theſe terrors, but it is not through any true ſetled peace that they have, but only a ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſtupid ignorance of their own danger, they are like a man aſleep on the top of a Maſt, do but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake them to ſee their danger, and it is enough to affright them into the infernal abyſs. While they go on quietly in ſin, they are but as a man which hath bribed the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant, which doth not pay his debt, nor ſecure him againſt Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, his debt increaſes ſtill, and he will have more to pay when he is arreſted. It is not a Merchants putting off the melancholick thoughts of his debts by pleaſures and divertiſements that will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes quiet his mind, he doth but
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:50143:42"/>beguile himſelf, and increaſe his debt, it is the acquitiance of his Creditor that can only ſecure him. This is the caſe of many, that when they are haunted, as <hi>Saul</hi> by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil ſpirit of an accuſing Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as he had his muſick to quiet his mind, they muſt have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to divert their thoughts from ſuch diſquieting and tormenting objects; but theſe are but like <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piates,</hi> which may ſtupifie for a time, and free from pains, but do nothing to the cure of the diſeaſe. It is only the blood of Chriſt that can <hi>ſprinkle our hearts from an evil Conſcience, cleanſe our Conſciences from dead works,</hi> only an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Faith that applies this blood to the Conſcience. So that the Heathen Philoſophers by all their preſcriptions could never quiet the Conſciences of ſinners, and all that peace that they had was only from ignorance of that ſevere inexorable juſtice of God, (which will never pardon ſin with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſatisfaction, and never be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified but by the ſufferings of Jeſus
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:50143:43"/>Chriſt) and the nature of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, or the condition of the Goſpel, that none ſhould have any benefit by Jeſus Chriſt but thoſe who are united with him by an effectual Faith which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duceth the fruits of holineſſe in a blameleſſe upright converſation; ſo that as the blood of Chriſt is the cauſe of our reconciliation with God, by Faith and holineſſe, we actually patake and are aſſured of the fruits thereof: all theſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are in ſeveral reſpects neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to true peace of Conſcience. Morality therefore can never teach a right way and means of it, to which the righteouſneſſe of faith is an hidden myſtery. The looſe prophane Chriſtan can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver attain it, while his converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is evidently inconſiſtent with that true faith and Goſpel ſince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which is abſolutely required of all that will be ſaved; and how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they may flatter or cheat themſelves into a vain preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or ſhut their eyes that they may not ſee their danger, they are
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:50143:43"/>continually obnoxious to the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frights and alarms of ſuch places of Scripture, as affirm that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out holineſſe none ſhall ſee God, that <hi>if we live after the fleſh we ſhall dye;</hi> that <hi>the Gate is ſtrait, and the way narrow that leads to life, and there are few that find it,</hi> that <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhall ſeek to enter, and ſhall not be able:</hi> That <hi>if any will be Chriſts Diſciple, he muſt deny himſelf and take up his Croſs and follow him:</hi> That <hi>whoever ſayes he knows God, and keeps not his Commandments, or that he hath communion with God, and walks in darkneſſe, is a lyar, and the truth is not in him:</hi> That <hi>whoever ſeems to be Religious, and bridleth not his tongue, his Religion is vain:</hi> That <hi>he that loves Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or Mother, or Wife, or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, or Houſe, or Lands, more than Chriſt, is not worthy of him.</hi> Beſides, others clearly importing, that a Man may have much knowledge, and his judgment ſo far convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, as to approve of the beſt things; may be much in holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, take delight in them, hear the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:50143:44"/>word with joy, do many things which he hears, be blameleſs as to his outward carriage, and yet be an hypocrite. So that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out daily exerciſing our ſelves to Godlineſſe, and a ſtrict watch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all our wayes, it is impoſſible to maintain a ſetled well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed peace of Conſcience. If any object that there are none more diſquieted in their Conſciences, than thoſe that make the greateſt ſhew of Religion, none more me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchollick and moroſe in their converſation; I may anſwer, <hi>ſolid joy is a ſerious thing,</hi> (as <hi>Seneca</hi> could ſay) it is not moſt ſeen in a forced laughter and jollity, which is as <hi>thorns under a pot, Eccl.</hi> 7.6. that for the preſent makes a great noiſe and blaze, but nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heats nor laſts. In the <hi>midſt of it the heart</hi> many times <hi>is ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and the end of it is heavineſſe,</hi> and, <hi>as the heart knows its own ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, the ſtranger intermeddleth not with its joy.</hi> There is that comfort within, which every one cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve. A Godly man needs not
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:50143:44"/>have his heart revived with wine, and ſtrong drink, and merry com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, like a ſick Man that is forced continually to have his ſpirits kept up with Cordials: He hath that within, which is better to him than Wine and Muſick. It is true, Godly Men have more inward conflicts in their Conſciences than others, but this proceeds from the ſenſe that they have of their own danger, as they ſay, <hi>Wiſdone armes miſery againſt it ſelf,</hi> that is, diſcovering the evils that we are obnoxious to, makes a Man more timerous and ſuſpicious, whiles <hi>fools go on and are puniſhed</hi> without any fear of danger, <hi>go on as an Ox to the Slaughter, a fool to the Stocks, a Bird to the ſuare, and knows not that it is for her life.</hi> It is time for a Man that knows, if he be not ſet upon the Rock that is higher than himſelf, if he be not upon that ſure Foundation, Jeſus Chriſt, he hangs by the ſmall thread of a brittle life, over the bottomleſſe pit, to look about him, and make his calling and election
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:50143:45"/>ſure. Again the greater eſteem any one hath of Heavenly things, the more careful he is to make ſure of them, the more fearfull to be deceived about them, (<hi>Tarda ſolet magnis rebus in eſſe fides.</hi>) And further, when Satan, who before kept all things in peace, ſees him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in danger of being diſpoſſeſſed, he rageth the more, as he rent the poor man out of whom he was caſt almoſt to death. And God gives him leave ſometimes to win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now his deareſt Children for their tryal; but for the moſt part God leaveth them to ſuch diſquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſpirit, and terrors of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience for ſome ſin, which they have fallen into, (as in <hi>Davids</hi> caſe) and then their trouble is not becauſe of their piety, but of their defect in it; or elſe it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he intends to raiſe them to ſome great eminency, or fill them with ſome extraordinary joy: as we may obſerve, where Men have been raiſed exceeding high, their foundation hath been laid very low in ſome deep abaſement, and
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:50143:45"/>ſo God brings them <hi>as a King our of Priſon to reign;</hi> and ordinarily when God layes his people low, either by extraordinary outward afflictions, or inward temptations, he doth recompence them for it by thoſe inward conſolations, which are the fore-taſts of Heaven; hence proceeds that <hi>joy</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, which is <hi>unſpeakable and full of Glory;</hi> which he that hath taſted the ſweetneſſe of it, would not want to be exempted from all thoſe Temptations and tryals which he hath been exerciſed with. The peace of wicked Men is but an <hi>agreement with Hell, which ſhall be diſanulled; a Covenant with death, which ſhall be broken,</hi> as the mirth of a Drunken Man, who whilſt his ſpirits are raiſed, feels not his wounds, but afterwards feels the ſmart of them, when his reaſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns to him. That will be the woful end of the carnal mans ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, if he be laid in the Bonds or Fetters of afflictions, and ſo come to himſelf and feel the wounds which he hath by ſin made in his
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:50143:46"/>own conſcience, he is a <hi>Magor miſſa bib,</hi> terror round about; that is the reaſon of ſuch horror many times on ſick beds, which yet is better than to be huſhed aſleep by the charming pleaſures of ſin, and not awake till he be amidſt the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting flames. So that we may ſay with the Prophet. <hi>The work of righteouſneſſe is peace, and the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecti of righteouſneſs, quietneſs and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance for ever.</hi> It is only by the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of Jeſus Chriſt, imputed to us by faith, that we have peace with God, and ſo peace of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, which is as <hi>a continual feaſt</hi> daily to entertain us, as a <hi>brazen wall,</hi> alwayes to ſecure us, that we may alwayes ſind that within, wherewith we may ſolace our ſelves, and need not fear that any thing ſhall diſturb or diſquiet the <hi>tranquillity</hi> which we have in our own ſouls.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:50143:46"/>
               <head>SECT. IX. <hi>The reward which Godly Men have after this life, the chief advantage of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The excellency thereof demonſtrated from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, from the ſatisfaction which the Angels have in it, from the glory which wicked Men enjoy in this World, from the ſweet fore-taſts which Godly men have of it in this life. Wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, the glory of the body, the happineſs of the Soul, in the enjoyment of God, in communion with the whole number of perfected Saints, and that for ever.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ALL that I have hitherto ſaid of the advantage of Godly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is little in reſpect of what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains to be ſpoken. The eſtate of Man after this life is of more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant conſideration, as it is u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:50143:47"/>ſaid, there is no proportion betwixt finite and infinite, as there is betwixt two things that are fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, though at the greateſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in reſpect of their natures, quality, quantity: ſo there is a proportion between a <hi>minute</hi> and a <hi>thouſand years,</hi> and minutes may eaſily be multiplyed to ſuch a quantity; but there is no propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betwixt a <hi>thouſand years</hi> and <hi>Eternity.</hi> So that if the miſery of Chriſtians in this life were anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to wicked mens prejudice, and the happineſs of wicked men an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to their own deſires, and if both might live in theſe two dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent eſtates a thouſands years twice told; yea, and ſuppoſe that after this life wicked men were to be happy to ſeven, and Godly men but to eight, (as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſpeak of the degrees of heat and cold) or that Godly men ſhould be as miſerable as wicked men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating only one degree, yet the conſideration of an Eternity would eaſily praeponderate in comparing the ſeveral ſtates of theſe perſons.
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:50143:47"/>The Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>if in this life only we have hope, we are of all men the moſt miſerable,</hi> not that a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man hath more real joy or comfort in this life than a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly man, but we muſt conſider that the Apoſtle is diſputing againſt ſuch as denied the Reſurrection in a popular Rhetorical ſtile, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in words are not to be ſubjected to a rigid interpretation, but to be expounded in a greater latitude, and it is uſual in ſeveral languages to expreſſe a thing with the greater <hi>Emphaſis</hi> by the <hi>Superlative degres,</hi> as if he had ſaid, we are very miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable men, if our hope be only in this life. Again there may be an <hi>Emphaſis</hi> in the <hi>Pronoun; q. d. we</hi> who are the off-ſcouring of all things in the eyes of the World, and have in theſe times of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution run ſuch hazards and quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted our worldly enjoyments for the hopes of a glorious Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are miſerably deceived, if there be no Reſurrection. And further, though Chriſtians have that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and comfort in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward tribulations, which doth
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:50143:48"/>more than counterballance them, yet this joy is in hope of the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, and but an anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that joyful Reſurrection which hereafter they expect. And now I ſhall come to ſpeak ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the certainty of it, of the the nature of it, and of the ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of holineſs neceſſary to thoſe who would enjoy it, &amp; that we may raiſe our thoughts to hold ſome proportion with the greatneſſe of that glory, though it be not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for poor Mortals to have an adequate conception thereof. <hi>Firſt,</hi> let us conſider the great things that God himſelf hath ſpoken of it, and how he hath throughout the Scripture propounded it as a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and an abundant recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, for whatſoever we can do and ſuffer for him, in compariſon where with all the afflictions of this life, are but light and inconſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. The Apoſtle tells us, <hi>God is not aſhamed to be called the God of his people, having prepared a City for them.</hi> The preparations that he hath made for them, are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:50143:48"/>to the bounty and muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of ſuch a Majeſty; though they here mourn whilſt others re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce, and though he here make them bear the Croſs, whilſt his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Enemies wear the Crown. Now it would be much below the greatneſſe and glory of ſuch a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, to boaſt of his own gifts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the real worth of them, and flatter men into his ſervice by poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing them with high expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of great matters, which the enjoyment of will not anſwer the hopes which God himſelf hath drawn us into. And we may be moſt ſecure that he will not give ſuch advantage to any Creature to enter into judgment with him. Now let us conſider what ſome of us have ſeen in the interviews, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of Princes, the Coronation or marriage of Kings, or on other occaſions, yet we have heard of more than we have ſeen. We have heard of the Glory of <hi>Solomon,</hi> and many other great Princes, exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what our times have to boaſt of, and yet we can enlarge our
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:50143:49"/>thoughts to ſomething above theſe, and let our minds wander into the four corners of the earth, to fetch in the Glory and ſplendor of the World; to make up to our ſelves an <hi>Idea</hi> of happineſſe, and yet when we have framed ſuch an <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> ſuch an imaginary Glory, God (who is too great, and too good, to deceive poor mortals) hath given us to underſtand that his preparations for his Saints are ſomewhat above all this, and that <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, non the heart of Man conceived what he hath laid up for thoſe that love him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the next place, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that it is the bleſſed ſtate of Angels, which are firſt of more en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged capacities than Men, and yet they find a perfect felicity therein. We ſhould not make a judgment of the ſtate, and magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence of a Princes Court, by the reports of ſome poor Peaſant, who (we might eaſily imagine) would be ready to admire any thing which he ſhould ſee above the pomp of his Landlords houſe,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:50143:49"/>where he uſed perhaps to labour, or go ſometimes to pay ſome poor rent, but we ſhould more eaſily believe ſome noble Courtier of a more raiſed mind, or ſome Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador that hath ſeen the pomp of ſeveral Princes Courts, and knows what belongs to State and greatneſſe. It had been no great matter to have heard <hi>Paul</hi> boaſt of what he ſaw in Paradiſe, who was carryed from theſe poor Cottages of clay, to the Court of Heaven; like <hi>David</hi> from the Sheepfold to <hi>Sauls</hi> Court. But the Angels con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually adoring the Glory of their King, and ſinging perpetual <hi>Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujahs</hi> to him, doth eaſily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade that the Glory of the Coe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtial Court, is far above what mortal eyes ever ſaw. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the enlarged capacities of Angels, we may conſider that they are incorporeal, ſo that theſe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreal delights and pleaſures, which we have the moſt clear and lively apprehenſion of, make up none of their happineſſe; but, beſides ſuch delights, which its
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:50143:50"/>likely we ſhall not want in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, (there are more pure and ſpiritual delights, enough to make an Angel happy; which we can ſcarce conceive any thing of. A further conſideration, which may argue the happineſſe of that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtate, is the greatneſs and Glory of many wicked men here in this World. Let us but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, how the great ones of the Earth, many of which have been wicked men, do bash themſelves continually in Rivers of pleaſure, and enjoy for many years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whatever their hearts can wiſh, and what we ordinarily ſee great ones now enjoy is little to the Glory of a <hi>Belſhazzer,</hi> a <hi>Dari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> an <hi>Alexander,</hi> a <hi>Ner<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> the <hi>Grand Signior,</hi> the Kings of <hi>China;</hi> and yet all this is but as the crumbs that fall from the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens table. What then can we imagine them to be fed with? theſe are but the ſpillings, or the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings of his bounty to his very Enemies: how great then is that which he hath reſerved for
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:50143:50"/>thoſe, to whom he hath purpoſed to <hi>ſhew the exceeding Riches of his Grace,</hi> to give the World a proof of his bounty and Glory? as a Prince that would make an enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment for oſtentation, and ſhew his great reſpect to ſome of his ſpecial and moſt beloved friends. We read often in Scripture of the preparations that God hath made for his Saints, which is but a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphorical expreſſion of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of that glory, which he hath ordained them to; as thoſe enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainments which Men do long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare for, do far exceed what they on a ſudden make, being unawares ſurprized by the coming of their friends. I will yet add another proof of the greatneſſe of that Glory, which we hope for; taken from the fore-taſts, which many have of it here, which hath made them Glory in tribulations, tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in the flames, and not only abated, but wholly taken away the ſenſe of the moſt exquiſite tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that ſome <hi>Martyrs</hi> have felt no more in the fire, than if they
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:50143:51"/>had been in a bed of Roſes. Some after long conflicts and terrors, have had ſuch raviſhing joys, that they have cryed to God to hold, they could bear no more. If ſuch glimpſes have ſo raviſhed them, what is the full view and clear viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Let us imagine a confection, the leaſt drop of which diſtilled into a draught of Gall, or Wormwood, or whatever can be ſuppoſed to be more bitter and diſtaſtful, ſhould wholly alter the taſt of it, making it moſt pleaſing and delicious, how ſweet would a full draught of it be without the leaſt mixture of any thing diſtaſtful and unpleaſing: ſo if ſuch drops of ſpiritual joys are able to ſweeten the bittereſt cup of afflictions, what ſhall we think of bathing our ſelves, and drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our fill in thoſe Rivers of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure at Gods right hand for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, without the leaſt mixture of any ſorrow or trouble to allay the ſweetneſſe thereof?</p>
               <p>I have hitherto in general ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the <hi>Glory of Heaven</hi> is like to be very great and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:50143:51"/>much more inexpreſſible, but I have not yet attempted to ſhew what it is, or wherein it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts, and while I ſay it is not to be expreſſed, if I ſhould go about to ſet it forth fully, there would be <hi>contradictio in terminis,</hi> ſo that all I dare pretend to, is ſome rude delineation of that ſtate of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Man is made up of two eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential parts, Soul and Body, now though the Soul be the more noble part, yet doubtleſſe the body ſhall have its ſhare in this felicity. If God hath ſo far honoured them, as to make them the <hi>Temples of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and given Chriſt a charge that he ſhould loſe <hi>nothing</hi> of what he hath given him, but raiſe up our ſcattered duſt at the laſt day, <hi>Job.</hi> 6.39. he hath cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly reſerved a reward for that which hath had ſo great a ſhare in our ſufferings here; and he hath told us in general, that he will by his Divine power <hi>change our vile bodies, and make them like his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body,</hi> but ſure as we approach nearer to the nature of God in
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:50143:52"/>our ſouls, ſo they ſhall have the greateſt ſhare of future Glory, and in general it ſhall be with the Glory wherewith Chriſt was glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied from Eternity, and after his ſuffering, and this ſhall be by the <hi>enjoyment</hi> of God, which is <hi>the acting of the perfected faculties and affections of our Souls upon him.</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very ſenſe hath its proper object in the enjoyment of which it takes complacency according to the ſuitableneſſe of the object thereto, and according to the nature of the <hi>object,</hi> and the capacity of the ſenſe for receiving it, or acting upon it, ſuch is the pleaſure that it finds therein, and the more noble the faculty and the object are, the more noble is the delight which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſeth from the Union betwixt them, ſo that all Philoſophers are agreed, that intellectual delights exceed ſenſual pleaſures. Now in Heaven our Souls ſhall be perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the capacity of a finite being; otherwiſe they would be no more capable of enjoying God, than a deaf man of being
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:50143:52"/>delighted with muſick, or a blind man in the moſt perfect beauty, therefore we are ſaid <hi>to be made meet, to be partakers of an inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance with the Saints in light; ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification,</hi> qualifying us <hi>naturally</hi> for Heaven, as <hi>juſtification</hi> doth <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally;</hi> and God himſelf ſhall be the object of our happineſſe, whom we ſhall ſee as he is, and love him, and delight in him according to his goodneſſe and glory; I know it is hard for us to conceive what it is to enjoy God, but to help us in the conception of it, let us conſider a little what it is to enjoy a friend, to have an abſent friend is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, but to be with him is a great addition to our contentment, to receive the expreſſions of their love, and to teſtifie ours to them. Thoſe who are of a more noble and generous complexion, find more true ſatisfaction herein, than in whatever elſe this World can afford them, and what is it that endears another to us, but <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Lovelineſſe?</hi> where there are amiable endowments in perſons of
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:50143:53"/>worth, they command an eſteem from us, though they know us not, and though we are never the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for them; but where they have a particular affection to us, take us into their boſom, make us of their entire friends, this doth much more endear them to us. Now (as I have already ſaid) we find in God, in a far more eminent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, that which renders the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures amiable and lovely. Beſides his <hi>goodneſſe</hi> towards the whole Creation, which the Earth is full of, his ſpecial favour to Mankind, and it may be to us above many thouſands of others; the <hi>exceeding Riches of Grace</hi> towards the <hi>Elect,</hi> which Men and Angels ſhall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire to the days of Eternity, there is that <hi>Beauty</hi> (that is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual beauty, or ſuch Beauty as is objected to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) which will raviſh the whole intellectual Creation. His <hi>Wiſdom</hi> is unſearchable, his <hi>Power</hi> irreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his <hi>Grace</hi> and Clemency as far exceeding what is to be found in the Creature, as his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi>
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:50143:53"/>and <hi>Glory. Job</hi> had heard of God, but when he came to ſee him, abhorred himſelf to ſee the infinite diſtance betwixt the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Creator, and a poor Mortal; that durſt diſpute the caſe with him. Oh! what thoughts ſhall we have of God when we come to ſee him as he is? What aſtoniſhment will ſeize upon us? what confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will cover us when we ſee what a God it is, whoſe grace we have ſo oft deſpiſed, whoſe patience we have ſo long abuſed, whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity we have ſo boldly contemned, and yet ſee that he who had us al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes at his mercy, and could at his pleaſure avenge himſelf on us, ſhould pardon us for his own ſake, and make ſuch glorious preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for us? We ſhall then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly underſtand all the dimenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of his love, and continually as it were read the ſtories of it. We may the better conceive of it by fancying to our ſelves, what a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular favour it would be to have ſome great Prince take a ſingular affection to us, though we did the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:50143:54"/>leaſt of any in the World deſerve it, and had diſ-obliged him by a thouſand provocations, if he ſhould take us home to his houſe, and maintain us alwayes at his table, keep us alwayes in his preſence, this would fall infinitely ſhort of that love which God will manifeſt to us, and what an addition will it be to our happineſſe to ſee him in his Glory, who hath loved us, and waſhed us from our ſins in his blood? the ſtory of whoſe love we have ſo oft read over, a ſight of whoſe Face though but through the Glaſs of Faith we have ſo oft, ſo long deſired and lamented a feer, to have the ſociety of the innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable company of Angels, and the general aſſembly of juſt men made perfect, a meeting of the Saints of all Ages and places, and theſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected both in Grace and Glory, ſo that they ſhall have no infirmities, no Pride, Ignorance, ſelf-ſeeking to exerciſe our charity or patience; no ſufferings to move our pity, or compaſſion; and we ſhall never need to diſquiet our ſelves with
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:50143:54"/>the thoughts of ſuch a ſad parting as <hi>Paul</hi> had, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.39. We ſhall keep an <hi>everlaſting Holy-Day,</hi> the marriage of the Lamb ſhall be for ever celebrated by all his Friends, and as <hi>Eternity</hi> will perpetuate our happineſſe, and make it the greater <hi>extenſivè,</hi> ſo the aſſurance and conſideration hereof will heighten it, and make it greater <hi>intenſivè,</hi> and every moment of our felicity will be more ſweet to us, in that we ſhall never be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieted with the thoughts that our condition (as happy as it is) will one day have an end.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:50143:55"/>
               <head>SECT. X. <hi>The neceſſity of holineſs to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, proved by many plain Scriptures. Objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons anſwered. The impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of being but formal half Chriſtians, and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that ſtict ſerious Chriſtians have above ſuch.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is yet another conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which will much enhance the glory of Heaven; but before I come to ſpeak of that, I muſt ſhew how neceſſary an holy converſation is to the enjoyment of it. Many have entertained a ſuſpition, that ſome moroſe Men peeviſhly envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt the happineſſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of Mankind, and too ſuperſtitiouſly preciſe, would lay upon them a yoke which neither they, nor their Fathers were able to bear, confining their liberty to too narrow bounds, and fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them from Religion by exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:50143:55"/>ſo much ſtrictneſſe and ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Now that I may not ſeem to any to make the way to Heaven more narrow than God hath made it, I will but ſet down the plain words of God himſelf, not to ſpeak of what thoſe have attained to, who yet are plainly declared to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſentence of condemnation, and in a ſtate of wrath. I ſhall only inſtance in ſome places where the Scripture ſets down what is indiſpenſibly neceſſary to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or what doth plainly argue, a Man to be in the ſtate of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Math.</hi> 5.20. <hi>I ſay unto you, that except your righteouſneſſe exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees,</hi> (who yet went a great way in the Profeſſion of Religion, and in both Moral and Ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al righteouſneſſe) <hi>you ſhall in no wiſe enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Cap. 6.20. <hi>Where your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure is, there will your heart be alſo.</hi> Cap. 7.13. <hi>Enter ye in at the ſtrait Gate, for wide is the Gate, and broad is the way that leads to deſtruction, and there be many which go in thereat; but
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:50143:56"/>ſtrait is the Gate, and narrow is the Way that leads to life, and few there be that find it.</hi> Verſe 21. <hi>Not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, but he that doth the will of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> cap. 12.36. <hi>Every idle word that a man ſhall ſpeak he ſhall give an account thereof in the Day of Judgment.</hi> Cap. 16.24. <hi>If any Man will come after me, let him deny himſelf, and take up his Croſs and follow me.</hi> Mark. 8.38. <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall be aſhamed of me, and of my words in this adulterous and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Generation, of him alſo ſhall the Son of Man be aſhamed when he comes in the Glory of the Father with his holy Angels.</hi> Luk. 13.24. <hi>Strive to enter in at the ſtrait Gate, for many I ſay, unto you ſhall ſeek to enter, and ſhall not be able.</hi> John. 3.5. <hi>Except a Man be born of water, and of the ſpirit, be cannot enter into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God.</hi> Rom. 8.9. <hi>If any Man have not the ſpirit of Chriſt, he is none of his.</hi> Verſe. 13. <hi>If ye live af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh ye ſhall dye,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.17. <hi>If any M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſt, he is a new
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:50143:56"/>Creature.</hi> Gal. 5.6. <hi>For in Chriſt Jeſus neither circumciſion avails any thing, nor uncircumciſion, but Faith that worketh by love.</hi> Cap. 6.7, 8. <hi>Be not deceived, God is not mocked, for whatſoever a Man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap; for he that ſoweth to the fleſh, ſhall of his fleſh alſo reap corruption, but he that ſoweth to the ſpirit, ſhall of the ſpirit reap life e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting.</hi> Heb. 12.14. <hi>Follow peace with all men and holineſs, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which no man ſhall ſee the Lord.</hi> Jam. 2.19, 20. <hi>Thou believeſt there is one God, thou doſt well: the Devils alſo believe and tremble. But wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thou know, O vain man, that faith without works is dead?</hi> 1 Pet. 4.18. <hi>If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ſinner and the ungodly appear?</hi> 1 John 1.6. <hi>If we ſay we have fellowſhip with him, and walk in darkneſſe, we lye and do not the truth.</hi> Cap. 2.4. <hi>He that ſaith I know him and keepeth not his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, is a lyar, and the truth is not in him.</hi> I might add many like words out of the Scripture of truth, but it may be theſe are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:50143:57"/>to make many ſay, <hi>Who then can be ſaved?</hi> But let God be true whatever becomes of Man, and it is that which hath been told us, that few find the narrow way that leads to life. If any object the failings of ſuch as <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> the ſame Scriptures that tell of them, tell us of their repentance and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter tears. If any wonder how this ſhould be conſiſtent with the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, I anſwer there are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther objects whereon he ſheweth the Riches of his mercy, even the ſmall remnant that ſhall be ſaved. And when we come to ſee (at the laſt day) the evil of ſin, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of God, the preparations which God hath made for ſinners, we ſhall rather admire that he ſhould ſave any, than that he ſhould ſave no more. And if the pardon of ſin were ſuch a light matter that God ſhould be charged with ſeverity, if he hearken not to the <hi>cries</hi> of <hi>ſinners,</hi> which neceſſity doth at laſt force them to, he might have ſpared the trouble (as I may take li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to ſpeak) of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ending his ſon;
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:50143:57"/>yea, (as I may further ſay) <hi>ſpared</hi> his glorying of his unconceivable love in giving Chriſt to dye for ſinners, and it is an ignorant conceit to think that ſuch a ſtrict exaction of holyneſſe ſtraitens the grace of the Goſpel when it is much of the Grace we receive by Chriſt to be <hi>turned from our iniquities, Acts</hi> 3.26. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The end of our redemption is to be a <hi>peculiar people zealous of good works. Tit.</hi> 2.14. The chief article of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace is to have the <hi>Law of God written in our hearts, Heb.</hi> 8.9. our chief glory to be <hi>like our heavenly Father in holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.15. The great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage we have by the promiſes to be made <hi>Partakers of the Divine Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> 2 <hi>Per.</hi> 1.4. So that let men flatter themſelves with vain pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions, and delude their own ſouls by drawing their deſires into opinion, and from wiſhing, they might have peace, though they go on in the wayes of their own hearts, proceed to believe that it will be ſo. <hi>Theſe words will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:50143:58"/>take hold of them,</hi> Zach. 1.6. <hi>and judge them at the laſt day.</hi> I may further add, that it is the greateſt imprudence for men to be but half Chriſtians, or to make ſome profeſſion of Religion, and not to ſtrive to attain to ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in it, both as the reflection on ſuch an indifferency, or luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmneſs, will be an aggravation of <hi>Mens</hi> miſery, while they ſhall think with themſelves they were near to the Kingdom of Heaven, and were ſhut out becauſe they went not a little further, they were fair for ſtriking a bargain for the <hi>Rich Pearl,</hi> and yet parted for a ſmall matter. As if a Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant ſhould go near to <hi>Peru,</hi> or ſome other place where there is Gold in abundance, and through a ſluggiſh lazy ſtupidity, come back empty; or as if <hi>Columbus,</hi> when he was near to the Coaſts of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merica,</hi> ſhould have been forced, through the mutiny of his Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to return and loſe the honour and advantage of his enterprize. It is pity to run a race, and loſe
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:50143:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>the prize through negligence, when we come within a few ſteps of the Goal. If we will do any thing in Religion, let us go through with it, and not loſe the future reward of it, which is moſt conſiderable through ſloathful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And it is further to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, that thoſe who are but half Chriſtians and ſmatterers in Religion, know nothing of thoſe ſpiritual comforts, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in communion with God in his ordinances, joy in the Holy Ghoſt, which thoſe who are truly Godly have experience of: thoſe who are but ſmatterers or bunglers in any Art, Science, Trade, find them difficult, when they are eaſie and delightful to thoſe who are Maſters of them, and throughly underſtand them; as the wiſe Man ſaith, <hi>knowledge is eaſie to him that underſtands.</hi> As there is great difference in the reading of a <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,</hi> Author by the <hi>Maſter</hi> and the <hi>Schollar,</hi> the <hi>Schollar</hi> looks upon it as a great task to conſtrue it, and is glad when it is over, not minding
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:50143:59"/>the things themſelves expreſſed by the words, while the Maſter who minds the matter, and underſtands it well, is tranſported with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to obſerve the <hi>elegancy</hi> of <hi>ſtile, height</hi> of <hi>fancy, depth</hi> of <hi>judgment, ſtrength</hi> of <hi>reaſon, ſubtilty</hi> of <hi>Wit, candor</hi> of <hi>mind</hi> which is in the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. So, while a Man is but a Chriſtian in name, and hath but a form of Godlineſſe, the exerciſes of Religion are a burthen to him, and he doth them only as a task to eſcape Hell fire, as a School-boy gets his Leſſon to eſcape the Rod, but he that is a Chriſtian indeed, finds that ſweetneſſe in the word of God, that it is to him as <hi>honey and the honey comb, the joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing of his Soul.</hi> He is glad when he can ſteal an opportunity to pray; he finds ſo much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort in communion with God therein, and can ſay with Chriſt; it is <hi>his meat to do the will of his Heavenly Father,</hi> and the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his Conſcience is to him as a <hi>continual feaſt,</hi> and makes the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of holineſſe more pleaſant to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:50143:59"/>him, than all the delights of ſin are to a wicked man. And as it is in trading, he that doth not throughly underſtand his Trade, cannot make his beſt advantage of it to thrive by it, and ſo grows weary of it, or turns bankrupt; when he that is well ſeen in the myſtery of it, and knows how to improve every opportunity of gain, and ſo finds the benefit of it, makes a pleaſure of his buſineſſe, and will not be perſwaded to leave it off. So he that is but a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an in ſhew, and finds not that real advantage which others do of a ſtrict walking with God, nor any return of their formal heartleſſe prayers, grow weary of Religion, and at length it may be caſt it off, while the real ſerious Chriſtian by the Rich returns of his ſincere and fervent prayers, and the benefit which he finds by a cloſe walking with God, is ſo confirmed in his holy profeſſion, that nothing ſhall make him caſt it off, or think it a burden.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:50143:60"/>
               <head>SECT. XI. <hi>The miſery of wicked Men af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life demonſtrated from Scriptures, from the ſufferings of Godly Men here in this World, from terrors of conſcience in good and bad, from the Devils trembling at the thoughts of it, which they have not ſo much reaſon for as Man. The puniſhment of loſſe with the aggravations of it. The puniſhment of ſenſe exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite, without allay or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, without end.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Shall now proceed to that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſideration, which will make the happineſſe of Heaven much greater; yea which conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered apart, doth much com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the excellency of Holineſſe, and clearly demonſtrate how much
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:50143:60"/>it is the <hi>intereſt</hi> of <hi>mankind</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after it, <hi>damnum emergens</hi> is as much to be conſidered as <hi>lucrum ceſſans.</hi> We ſhould not only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>reward of Holineſſe,</hi> but the <hi>wages of ſin;</hi> if a ſinner could ceaſe to be, or might be annihila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted when he dyes, or if there were any ſtate between Heaven and Hell, our plea would have leſs force: but there will be but two ranks of Men at the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt judgment, whereof one ſhall go into <hi>eternal life,</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into <hi>everlaſting puniſhment. Mat.</hi> 25.46. Now I ſhall uſe the ſame method in conſidering this ſtate of ungodly men after the end of the World, which I followed in conſidering the ſtate of holy men. Firſt, giving ſome general demonſtrations of the miſery of it, then ſome particular reaſons why it will be ſo intollerable. As firſt, the Glory of Heaven may be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to be exceeding great by the preparations which God is ſaid to have made for it: ſo by the ſame <hi>Anthropopathy</hi> we may conceive of the miſery of Hell, God being ſaid
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:50143:61"/>to prepare the puniſhment of the damned. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.41. It is ſaid in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is <hi>prepared for the Devil and his Angels,</hi> but wicked men ſhall be co-heirs with them of the ſame miſery. He is laying up his <hi>pile of Fire and Wood. Iſa.</hi> 30.33. and laying ſinners as ſtubble in the Sun to dry, that the eternal flames may prey more furiouſly upon them, <hi>Nahum</hi> 1.10. ſuffering them to <hi>fill up the meaſure of their iniquity, and ſo to treaſure up to themſelves wrath againſt the day of wrath,</hi> that they may be <hi>fit for deſtruction.</hi> Let us in the next place conſider what Godly men have ſuffered in this Life, read but the <hi>Marryrologies</hi> and ſee the dreadful torments that the Martyrs have ſuffered, enough to make one tremble at the reading of them; and if theſe things be done to the green tree, thoſe who are the objects of Gods love, and dear unto him as the apple of his eye, ſuch on whom he hath deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to ſhew the Riches of his mercy, what will be done to the dry with whom he is <hi>angry every
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:50143:61"/>day,</hi> and on whom he will ſhew the <hi>power of his wrath? if judgment begin at the houſe of God, what will be the end of thoſe that obey not the Goſpel?</hi> Further, let us conſider the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors of Conſcience which Godly men have ſuffered in this World, when they have had lively appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the diſpleaſure of God againſt them. If his <hi>rebukes have made them conſume as a moth, fretting a garment,</hi> if his frowns have diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted them and made them <hi>roar through the diſquietneſſe of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> What will it be for his jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to ſmoak and his wrath to burn like fire for ever? Again, let us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what horrors wicked men have felt in their conſciences in this life, which are but the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſts of that miſery which they ſhall endure for ever. Read but the ſtories of <hi>Vaninus, Spira,</hi> &amp;c. who have dyed in deſpair, if ſuch drops of wrath let fall like ſcalding Lead upon the Soul, have ſo hide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly amazed and terrified, ſurely it is dreadful and aſtoniſhing to be <hi>caſt into the lake that burns with
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:50143:62"/>fire and brimſtone for ever.</hi> And though there be many now can harden themſelves againſt God; and think by a <hi>ſtoical apathy</hi> to bear whatever God can inflict, yet ſome have found the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Hell in their Conſciences, worſe a thouſand times than all the torments which the cruelty of Tyrants, or incarnate furies could ever invent. And whereas ſome may think (with <hi>Spira</hi>) that the expectation of future miſery, is worſe than the ſuffering of it, it is a wide miſtake, <hi>for according as M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n feareth, ſo is his anger,</hi> Pſal. 90.11. ordinary calamities indeed are for the moſt part worſe feared than felt, but when a man hath raiſed his mind to the moſt dreadful and amazing apprehemions of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure of God, and the ſeverity of his vengeance, he cannot reach the vaſtneſſe of it, there is yet <hi>à plus ultra,</hi> ſomewhat further, as it is in our apprehenſions of the Glory and happineſſe of Heaven: and at the laſt day the great and mighty men of the World, who have ſet
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:50143:62"/>the judgements of God far above, out of their ſight, and ſcorned his threats, as a meer <hi>brutum fulmen,</hi> or a <hi>Mormo</hi> to fright Chrildren and ſuperſtitious fools, would be glad if they knew how, to run un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Rocks and Mountains to hide themſelves from the terrible Majeſty of their Judge, and (to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude to the words of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.11. Let ſuch think that as God is now in his word when he ſeems to be abſent from them, ſuch will he be alſo indeed, when he ſhall manifeſt his preſence and his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous judgment. We begin to think meanly of all whom we can ſee through or go about, it is incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſibleneſs that commands a veneration, &amp; that we ſhall alwayes find in God both as to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Grace, and as to the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his Power and wrath. Let us yet go a ſtep further, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the apprehenſions which the <hi>Devils</hi> have of this condition, (for they and wicked men (as was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obſerved) are fellow heirs of the ſame miſery) and theſe tremble
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:50143:63"/>at the thoughts of it, that is, have dread full amazing apprehenſions at the expectation of it, the <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent</hi> in that place being put for the <hi>antecedent,</hi> according to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual <hi>phraſeology</hi> of Scripture; they ſeem not to have ſo much reaſon to be troubled at the thoughts of it as men have, their ſins perhaps may have ſome aggravations, which the ſins of Men have not; yet, I think there is nothing can aggravate it ſo as the contempt of the Goſpel, which they are not guilty of. They had not a <hi>board after Shipwrack,</hi> whereon they might have ſaved themſelves, if it had not been their own fault. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, they have no bodies to be tormented as we have, many can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not apprehend how the Soul ſhould be capable of any conſiderable torment, and they think they could laugh at any puniſhment that could be inflicted on the Soul, were it not for bodily ſufferings, which they have a clearer appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honſion, and a more lively ſenſe of: but, beſides all that we are capable
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:50143:63"/>of ſuffering in our bodies, we are capable of ſuffering the ſame in our ſouls, which the Devils are ſaid to tremble at the belief of, but it is with us, as it is with little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, who are pleaſed perhaps with the pomp of their Fathers or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Funeral, and proud of their mourning Cloaths, but are not ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of their own loſſe, when thoſe that are grown up to years of reaſon and judgement, wring their hands to think of what ſad conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence ſuch a loſſe will be to them. And in this reſpect it is ſaid, <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom arms miſery againſt it ſelf.</hi> We glory in that which is our ſhame, and the cauſe of our miſery, while the Devils tremble, who know what it is to loſe Heaven, (having been already in it) and know what Hell is, becauſe they have felt it, they certainly believe theſe things, having more underſtanding to apprehend the clear demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations of the truth of them, they have their minds more fixed on theſe things which are the matter of their torment being more in <hi>act</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:50143:64"/>and leſſe in <hi>Power</hi> than we are. We know not now what it is to loſe God and Heaven, but we ſhall know when we ſhall ſee them, not to <hi>enj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> them, but to <hi>envy</hi> them. We are ready to fla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ter our ſelves into hopes, that theſe things may not be tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e; or our thoughts are ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily diverted to other things. And the Devil keeps that out of our minds, which he knows not how to keep out of his own, leſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daring well of it, we ſhould be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced thereby to believe, and ſo obtain ſalvation, <hi>Luke</hi> 8.14. For a concluſion of theſe general demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations, I might add Chriſts im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Men to flee from the wrath to come, though through ſo many hardſhips and difficulties, which he calls them to: he wept over ſinners, and was grieved for the hardneſſe of their hearts, as ſometimes <hi>Jeremy</hi> was, or as <hi>Aidanus,</hi> a good man in this Nation, wept to think of the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries which were coming upon it. Sinners go on careleſly and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely, <hi>like an Ox to the Slaughter
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:50143:64"/>or a fool to the correction of the ſtocks,</hi> but Chriſt paſſionately pleads with them, to divert them from their own wayes, knowing how little they conſider the miſery of thoſe devouring flames, which they are caſting themſelves into. Now for proving more particularly, that this miſery which ungodly men ſhall endure, is very ſad and dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. Firſt, we ſhall not only know (as I before intimated) the worth of that Glory which we have loſt, but we ſhall be convinced that we have loſt it through our own fault. Many think now to harden them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves at the day of judgement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, and impeach him of rigor and injuſtice, if he ſhould doom them to an Eternal Hell, but then when their Conſciences are awakened, they will own their guilt, and ſay as <hi>Judas, I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Mat.</hi> 27.4. though he did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but by the <hi>determinate coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel and fore-knowledge of God,</hi> and that which <hi>Satan had put into his heart.</hi> John 13.2. Act. 2.23. And it will be an aggravation of Mens
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:50143:65"/>miſery, that they ſhould loſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven through their own careleſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and exchange it for a trifle: ſhould a Man have a dear Wife dangerouſly ſick, and give her poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to kill her, inſtead of Phyſick to cure her, meerly through his own negligence, ſurely he would bury himſelf with her, when he ſhould ſee his own overſight, or ſhould he in a drunken fit ſtab his Children, certainly his firſt work after he ſhould come to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, would be to ſtab himſelf; but what are theſe to our ſouls, our <hi>darlings,</hi> our only ones <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.10. which we wound worſe than the poor Lunatick man, that cut himſelf with ſtones: we ſhall come to our ſelves, and have far different ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of all things, as ſoon as our ſouls look out of theſe dark priſons of our bodies, and begin to ſee by the light of another World. A child that ſhould have the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of a fair Eſtate, and ſell them for trifles, looking but upon the bulk of paper or parchment, not regarding the contents of them,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:50143:65"/>and afterwards when he comes to be a Man, ſhould live in diſgrace and miſery, whiles he ſees another bear high in the World with his Eſtate, would bewail too late his own childiſh vanity; but what is this to our ſelling of our hopes of Heaven for the pleaſures of ſin, in the midſt of which <hi>the heart is ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful,</hi> and <hi>the end of which is hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vineſſe?</hi> regarding the Goſpel no more than a ſtory out of <hi>Pliny,</hi> looking on the Scriptures but as waſt papers, <hi>Cleopatra's</hi> prodigali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in drinking a little Pearl at one draughtt was nothing to ours, we were never put to it as <hi>Liſyma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus,</hi> to loſe a Kingdom, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject our ſelves to perpetual ſlavery for a draught of water. Oh! with what indignation ſhall we reflect upon our own folly and madneſſe, when we ſhall have time and occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to ſettle theſe things in our hearts, we ſhall need no Devils to torment us, no fire to burn us, our own conſciences will continually ſcourge us, and we ſhall for ever be our own tormenters, when we
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:50143:66"/>ſhall be awakened to <hi>ſmite upon our thigh and ſay, what have I done?</hi> there will be yet a further puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſenſe, the Scripture calls it Fire and Brimſtone, which if we underſtand literally, and in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per ſenſe, we may eaſily imagine the dreadfulneſſe of ſuch a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or at leaſt learn to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it by holding our hand in a hot furnace but for one minute, and this is fire, which ſhall not ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly devour or annthilate us (as ſome imagine) but prey eternally upon men, and never conſume them, otherwiſe the Devils, with whom (as I have obſerved) we ſhall ſhare in the ſame miſery would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoyce, than tremble at the thoughts of the laſt judgement, if they ſhould then be preſently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to nothing. See more of this in <hi>Auſtin De civitate Dei. lib.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 10. But if we underſtand this figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively, or metaphorically, then certainly God hath choſen that which is the moſt exquiſite pain, which we can conceive of, to ſet forth ſomething elſe which we
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:50143:66"/>know not how otherwiſe to frame a notion of in our minds, and which doth as far exceed ſuch ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible things, as are uſed to expreſs it, as the Glory of Heaven doth exceed all that Glory which is borrowed from the Creatures to expreſs it to our weak imperfect underſtandings. Further, this puniſhment will be without any al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lay, in Hell there is pure darkneſs, there will not be a drop of water allowed to refreſh in thoſe raging flames, and company which ſome talk of, will but increaſe mens torment; and as there will be no allay, ſo no intermiſſion, no <hi>lucida intervalla,</hi> as there will be no <hi>night of Darkneſſe</hi> in Heaven, ſo there will be no <hi>night of reſt</hi> in Hell, and to compleat the miſery of that condition, there will be no end of it. Eternity will make their miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perpetual, but the belief and conſideration of eternity will make it inſupportable, and ſwallow Men up in a hideous deſpair, they ſhall be like men t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the midſt of the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, the Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing one af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:50143:67"/>another, if he could ſee any land behind thoſe proud ſurges, there might be ſome hopes; but to ſee nothing but the vaſt Ocean, and the Waves ſwelling higher and higher, and raging againſt him like a Giant, this is that which amazeth him: and ſuch will the thoughts of Eternity be then to miſerable ſinners, when lifting up their heads to ſee if they can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcry any end of their miſery, they ſhall ſee thouſands of Ages multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying themſelves to infinity, and there will be no remedy left, but they muſt ſink down into an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting deſpair; neither will time or ſuffering at all alleviate their miſery, as the Poet ſaith of thoſe, who by enduring poverty make it at length more eaſie to be born: as our multiplyed thoughts of the happineſſe of Heaven, will not cloy and weary, but increaſe our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and fruition; ſo will our thoughts of torment, more enrage thoſe eternal flames which ſhall burn within us, and make that burning ſurnace glow more and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:50143:67"/>more, that as the duration of mens miſery draws it forth <hi>extenſively,</hi> ſo it will alſo aggravate it <hi>inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively,</hi> till it come to that extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, beyond which there can be imagined, no degrees to which it may be further heightened.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XII. <hi>How much Religion conduces to the good of humane Soci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties. And firſt, of Families, preſcribing ſuch rules to all therein, as well obſerved, would make them happy in each other.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>IF thou be wiſe, thou ſhalt be wiſe for thy ſelf,</hi> ſaith the wiſeſt of Men. <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.12. He that hath the fear of God, which is the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or chief and principal of all wiſdom, doth (as is evident from what hath been ſaid already) beſt provide for himſelf, and conſult his own ſoveraign good, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed God hath out of his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:50143:68"/>goodneſſe to mankind, ſo twiſted and interwoven their hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe with his own glory in the buſineſſe of our ſalvation, that while they beſt ſerve him, they do moſt advantage themſelves, and according as they ſeek his Glory, they promote their own happineſs; but yet we are not born for our ſelves, but as every member ſhould do its office for the common good of the whole body, ſo every Man ſhould as a member of the univerſe or community, ſtand the whole in ſome ſtead, and not be as a <hi>Wen</hi> or a <hi>Wolf,</hi> a diſeaſe or deformity only drawing away nouriſhment from the body, without doing it any ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, being an unprofitable burden of the earth, <hi>living undeſired, dying unlamented.</hi> Wherefore I will now come to conſider <hi>Man</hi> as a <hi>ſociable creature;</hi> and as he ſtands in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to others, and ſo we ſhall find that a <hi>good Man is a common good,</hi> and that Religion and holineſſe doth not only make men <hi>Tzadikim,</hi> or <hi>juſt</hi> but <hi>Chaſidim,</hi> or <hi>good,</hi> for which (if for any) men will ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:50143:68"/>their lives. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7. And firſt, I ſhall conſider <hi>Men</hi> in an <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conomical ſtate.</hi> Families being the firſt in order among the Societies of Men, others being made up of a conjunction, or combination of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral families, as families are made up of ſeveral perſons. Now in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies there is a threefold ſociety.
<list>
                     <item>The 1. <hi>Conjugal</hi> between <hi>Husband</hi> and <hi>Wife.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 2 <hi>Paternal</hi> between <hi>Parents</hi> &amp; <hi>children.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>The 3. <hi>Deſpotical</hi> between <hi>Maſters</hi> &amp; <hi>ſervants</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Though all theſe not be found in every family, yet they are all found in ſome, and ſome in all. And let us but conſider the Rules preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to all theſe by Chriſt in the Goſpel, and we ſhall ſee a perfect draught of <hi>Oeconomicks,</hi> and the moſt exact pattern of an happy well governed Family. And if any profeſſing Godlineſſe do not come up to ſuch rules, what I have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to prove holds good in <hi>Theſi,</hi> and it is not Mens Godlineſſe, but their want of it which is to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; though we may find this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians, ſooner than
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:50143:69"/>
                  <hi>Plato</hi> find his <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> or the <hi>Stoicks</hi> their <hi>perfect man.</hi> For the <hi>Conjugal</hi> Society, <hi>Husbands</hi> are to love their <hi>Wives</hi> as themſelves, as their own bodies; yea, as Chriſt loved his Church, a proof of which he gave in giving himſelf for it, ſo that he is to provide for her what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever is meet and neceſſary, not to be bitter againſt her, to be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der towards her, giving honour to her, by how much more honour God hath given to him, to inſtruct her in whatever is meet for her to learn of him; and in a word to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake all others in the World, and cleave only to her, reckoning her and himſelf no more two but one fleſh. <hi>Wives</hi> on the other hand are obliged to ſubmit themſelves to their Husbands, to reverence them, to obey them, diligently and frugally to manage the affairs of their Family, and to eaſe their Husbands as far as may be of the burden of cares that lyes on them; and to carry themſelves, with that prudence, modeſty, chaſtity, gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, that they may be a Crown
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:50143:69"/>to their Husbands, that the heart of their Husbands may truſt ſafely in them, and that they may do them good, and no hurt all their dayes. So in the <hi>Paternal</hi> Society, <hi>Parents</hi> are bound to take care of the Souls of their Children, and to bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, to teach them the way wherein they ſhould walk, while they are young, and to take care of their bodies alſo, providing for them, laying up por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for them, and not to uſe too much rigor and ſeverity towards them, ſo as to diſcourage them, yet to give them that moderate cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, which the vanity of child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and youth many times makes neceſſary. So <hi>Children</hi> are to obey their Parents in all things lawful, to honour and reverence them, to requite their care of them, by maintaining them (if need require) in their Old Age concealing their infirmities, and abſtaining from all expreſſions of contempt and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpect. In the <hi>Deſpotical</hi> Society. <hi>Maſters</hi> are obliged to exerciſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:50143:70"/>towards their Servants, not ruling them with too much impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſſe, or rigor, conſidering they have a <hi>Maſter</hi> themſelves like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in Heaven, by whom they would not be dealt with, in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſeverity; they are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for them, to give them that which is juſt for their ſervice; yea, that which is reaſonable and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual, rewarding induſtry and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs with more than Servants can in ſtrictneſs require. So <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> are bound to ſubmit them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to their Maſters, not only in doing their work, but doing it in ſimplicity and ſingleneſſe of heart, as to God, conſidering it as a duty which they owe to God, as well as to Man, and that they muſt look for their recompence from him, ſo they muſt ſtudy to pleaſe their Maſters, not provoking by rude or croſs anſwers, not purloyning or waſting unneceſſarily their Maſters goods, not taking of their time, which is their Maſters, to ſpend in their own ſervice, or in pleaſure, or idleneſſe. Oh! how happy
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:50143:70"/>would families be, if all therein did obſerve theſe rules? We ſhould have no complaints of the churliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or careleſſeneſs of <hi>Husbands,</hi> of the Prodigality and diſloyalty of <hi>Wives,</hi> of the harſhneſs or ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Maſters,</hi> of the undutifulneſs and unfaithfulneſſe of <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Servants.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XIII. <hi>How far Religion advances the happineſs of Kingdoms and Common-wealths, not only naturally, as it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes the beſt Laws, and rules to all ſorts of Perſons, and keeps Men within the bounds of their duty; But morally, as it brings down bleſſings, keeps off judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. The falſe accuſations which Chriſtians have lain under in all Ages.</hi> Julians <hi>wicked policy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw let us proceed to conſider Man in a <hi>Politick State,</hi> as
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:50143:71"/>part of a Kingdom or Common-Wealth: and if we would deſcribe ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia,</hi> or ſet down a Model of a happy well governed, flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Common-Wealth; we need go no further than the Scriptures for our <hi>maxims,</hi> and deſcribe the ſeveral members of it according to what the Goſpel requires that they ſhould be. I know the great ones of the World have been jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of the Kingdom of Chriſt, as <hi>Herod</hi> was troubled, when he firſt heard of his Birth. I know not what occaſion the abuſes of ſome Impoſters may have given to Mens prejudice and ſuſpition, but (as I ſaid before) that the obſervation of Chriſts precepts would prevent more diſeaſes, than his miracles cured, ſo I may boldly affirm that his ſpiritual Kingdom, were it ſet up in the World, (that is, did his Laws take place, and were they duely obſerved) they would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract more, and be more taking than his ſuppoſed earthly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, which made multitudes run after him in the dayes of his
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:50143:71"/>fleſh, <hi>John.</hi> 6. And it is the great honour of Religion, and an evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argument of the real worth and excellency of it, that not only thoſe whoſe corrupt affections have baffled their Judgements to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Religion is but a fancy, a deviſed fable, or at leaſt to wiſh and pretend it to be ſo, but the wiſeſt of ſuch men as have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the dictates of natural reaſon, and men whom none can imagine to have been fore-ſtalled with too favourable an opinion of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or to have been <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſuperſtitiouſly over-aw'd by a Deity,</hi> that theſe I ſay, ſuch as <hi>Plato, Plutarch, Tully, Seneca, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavel, Campanella,</hi> ſhould look upon it as ſuch a good Engine for moving the huge bodies of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and Common-Wealths; yea, a neceſſary <hi>baſis</hi> to found govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon, (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſheweth) without which it can no more ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, than a Caſtle or City in the air, it ſhews clearly that there is that propoſed in Religion, which if men according to their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:50143:72"/>can be but flattered into a belief of it will keep them in their due place and order, that every part of ſuch a vaſt <hi>Machina</hi> may move regularly. And it is a good obſervation of the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> that <hi>Rome</hi> had the happineſſe in the firſt founding of it, to have ſuch Kings ſucceſſively, as did by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees take care of ſuch things, as did moſt conduce to its flouriſhing and eſtabliſhment, and that when <hi>Romulus</hi> had built the City, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected a new Kingdom: <hi>Numa Pompilius</hi> did immediately ſucceed him, and eſtabliſh Religion and the worſhip of God ſo far, as the light of Nature would guide him thereto. And the truth is, the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of another life after this, and of ſome inviſible power, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior to the power of man, is ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely neceſſary for the ſwaying and managing thoſe two great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines of <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> which turn about the whole World, ſo that (as <hi>Campanella</hi> well obſerves) <hi>Religione e anima della Republica e diffeſa della legge naturale,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:50143:72"/>is the Soul of a Common-Wealth, and Bulwark of the Law of Nature,</hi> becauſe the Love and Fear of God, and of eternal puniſhment and rewards do compel Men to the obſervation of the Law. What will a man care for his Life, if he apprehend that there is none after this? and there is no means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain men from, whatever inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies or violences they may think neceſſary to the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their preſent life, if they do not look for an after-reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but they might well ſay, <hi>Let us eat and drink, for to morrow we ſhall dye,</hi> and rather contemn a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life, than omit any means for the bettering of it. <hi>He that ſets light by his own life, is Maſter of another mans,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> And we know the form of endictments in our own law for any crime, is, <hi>ſuch a one not having the fear of God before his eyes, did wickedly,</hi> &amp;c. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſuch an act. And <hi>Abraham</hi> thought when he was in <hi>Gerar</hi> that they would not ſtick at any the vileſt action, becauſe as he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:50143:73"/>
                  <hi>the Fear of God was not in that place Gen.</hi> 20.10. <q>So we find the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> in <hi>Lucretius Lib.</hi> 1. complaining of his being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aw'd by the ſuſpition which he had of an eternal puniſhment af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this life; if he could have been aſſured that there ſhould be no life after this, or that then there ſhould be an end of Mens ſufferings, he could eaſily laugh at Religion, and deſpiſe the threatnings of their <hi>Vates.</hi> But, ſeeing he knew not the nature of the Soul, whether it was propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated with the body, or infuſed, whether it did dye with the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, or were caſt into the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake, he could not free himſelf from the fears of an eternal mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery after Death.</q> But I will come more particularly to ſhew how Religion doth contribute to the happineſſe and welfare of the Societies of Men, ſetting the boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daries of every ones Duty, preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing to all from the higheſt to the loweſt, telling the great ones of the World, that <hi>they which rule
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:50143:73"/>over men, muſt be juſt, ruling in the fear of God,</hi> whoſe Kingdom is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all, who rules in the Kingdoms of men, and gives them to whom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever he will, and he makes them his <hi>Miniſters, not to be terrors to good works, but to evil. To be Fathers to the poor, and to ſearch out the cauſe which they know not, to break the jaws of the wicked, and pluck the ſpoil out of their teeth.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriors are thereby likewiſe inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to <hi>ſubmit themſelves to their ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, to give them due honour and tribute, to be Subject for Conſcience ſake,</hi> which is the beſt foundation of diſloyalty and fidelity. As <hi>Conſtantius</hi> would ſay, thoſe that would not be true to God, would not be true to him. If any ſhall here ſay, <hi>Quid verba audiam?</hi> We have found the contrary true, and have oft ſeen Religion made a Cloak to palliate Sedition and Rebellion. I might anſwer by an <hi>Antiſtrophe</hi> retorting the objection. It ſeems, Religion is good in it ſelf, becauſe it is made uſe of to palliate that which is evil: Men do not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:50143:74"/>ordinary ſtones, or Iron, but <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Pearls,</hi> as I have already upon occaſion obſerved. If Satan be transformed into an Angel of Light, what wonder if his Miniſters be ſometimes transformed into the Servants of God. I may again ſay with <hi>Tertullian, Si accuſaſſe ſat eſt, quis erit innocens?</hi> None can maintain their innocency, if upon a bare accuſation they ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, without a fair hearing. Not Chriſt himſelf. <hi>John.</hi> 19.12. Nor his followers. <hi>Acts</hi> 17.7. This odious crimination hath been uſed in ſeveral Ages, as the moſt effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al means to ſubject Chriſtians to the diſpleaſure of Princes, and to popular hatred, which they had ſome pretence for in thoſe times, when the Emperors enjoyned ſuch things by their authority as Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians did juſtly ſcruple, which oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned that wicked policy of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian,</hi> (that he might avoid the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of perſecution, which he ſaw was grown odious) to ſet the Heathen Idols by the Emperors ſtatue, that while they refuſed to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:50143:74"/>give <hi>Religious honour</hi> to the one, they might be accuſed of denying <hi>civil reſpect</hi> to the other.</p>
               <p>Let us now deſcend to conſider the aſpect that Religion hath upon fellow Citizens or Subjects, or how it conduceth to the mutual benefit and advantage of them. And firſt, let us conſider what an influence that general rule of Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. would have upon all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to bring back again the <hi>Golden Age,</hi> if when we have to do with others, we would put our ſelves into their condition, and conſider how we ſhould deſire to be dealt with in ſuch a caſe: How gently and tenderly would ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors carry themſelves towards their inferiors? and with how much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and obſervance would inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors carry themſelves to their ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors? the Rich would not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from the poor, when he had wherewith to relieve him, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply his wants, but would bring upon himſelf <hi>the bleſſing of him who is ready to periſh, and make the heart of the peor to rejoyce and ſing.</hi> The
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:50143:75"/>poor would not by his idleneſſe be unneceſſarily burdenſom to the Rich, or commit rapes upon his charity, but would labour diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his hands, and abate the allowance which men ordinarily give to their luſts, that ſo he might be in a capacity rather to give, than to receive. The lender would not take advantage of the neceſſity of the borrower, nor the borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ingratefully defraud the lender; the ſeller would not deceive or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver reach the buyer, nor the buyer undervalue the goods of the ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Conſider further, how Chriſt more particularly requires that we ſhould be like God in goodneſſe, doing good to all, forgiving inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and making their condition our own, ready to be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, for each other (as <hi>Ignatius</hi> oft ſpeaks) <hi>laying down our lives for our bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, dwelling in Love, which works no ill to her neighbor, envies not, vaunts not it ſelf, is not puffed up, behaves not it ſelf unſeemingly, ſeeks not her own, is not eaſily provoked, thinks no evil, rejoyceth not in iniquity, but in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:50143:75"/>the truth, bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, ſuffers all things.</hi> If ſuch commands of Chriſt were obſerved, Men might beat their ſwords into Plow-ſhares, their Spears into pruning hooks, there would be no leading into Captivity, no complaining in our Streets, no vexatious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, no groaning of the oppreſſed, no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity of poverty, or want to put Men upon violence, private inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, publick ſedition. If men would according to the command of Chriſt, obey their teachers, prove all things, hold faſt that which is good, prefer others in honour before themſelves, not thinking of themſelves above what is meet, not being wiſe in their own eyes, but humbly enquire after truth, ſuſpecting their own judgement, following after thoſe things which make for peace and edification, ſtudying to be quiet, letting their moderation be made known to all Men. And if thoſe that are Teachers and Rulers in the Church would not Lord it o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:50143:76"/>the heritage of God, but be gentle towards them, as a Nurſe to her Children, not ſeeking theirs but them, doing all things for their edifying; we ſhould ſoon ſee an end of diviſions and Schiſms, and ſeparations in the Church. If any here object that I fancy a Church of <hi>Cathariſts,</hi> and ſuch pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and holineſſe in Men, as is not to be expected in this World; I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, I ſpeak of what is rather to be <hi>deſired</hi> than <hi>hoped</hi> for, and what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion would do towards the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of Mankind, were the rules of it duely obſerved, and would Men be faithful to the principles of it, which is ſufficient to this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology,</hi> which I here make againſt ſuch as would reproach it, and bring it into diſgrace in the world, and to prove that the more Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion flouriſheth in any Nation, the happier it is, and the better order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that we may conclude with the <hi>Tragedian.</hi> Where <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, righteouſneſſe, holineſſe, piety and faithfulneſſe are neglected, that Kingdom cannot long ſtand,</hi> and if
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:50143:76"/>any think this would do well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, if all would agree to do thus. I anſwer, the neglect of others doth not diſcharge us from our duty, we owe it to God, though Men ſhould not deſerve it, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite it with a reciprocal care of Juſtice and equity. And further, it is a great advantage for raiſing our honour, when others neglect their duty. Sometimes ſingularity is the only means to get a name, as the <hi>Satyriſt</hi> could ſay,
<q>
                     <l>Aude aliquid brevibus gyaris aut car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere dignum</l>
                     <l>Si vis eſſe aliquid; probitas laudatur &amp; alget.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>There is yet another way, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by good men do promote the <hi>weal-publick,</hi> and that is by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation of children, which in well governed Common-Wealths there hath alwayes been a ſpecial care taken for. Thoſe are counted good Common-wealths-men that build and plant ſuch things as the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth may be the better for, and enjoy the furit of when
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:50143:77"/>they are dead and gone. But thoſe that ſtock the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth with Plants of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which may in future times bring forth the fruits of Juſtice and equity, do more promote the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, and thoſe who let go Foxes and Wolves are not more worthy of puniſhment, than ſuch as bring up Children in a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth, which through their fault and neglect of good educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, are addicted to nothing but idleneſs and luxury, and as Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives form and faſhion the head while the bones are tender, ſo Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents ſhould faſhion their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens minds, and form their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners while they are tender and plyant, which if then neglected, do very hardly afterwards yield to Diſcipline <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> or <hi>Civil.</hi> Thus far I have ſhewed how God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe doth promote the good of a Nation in a way of <hi>natural cauſali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> There is yet another way whereby it doth conduce thereto, and that is by a <hi>moral cauſality: God delivering often the Iſland of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:50143:77"/>which is delivered by the pure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his hands. Job.</hi> 22. 30. Theſe are as the Trees in a Cawſey, which having life and ſubſtance in them, though ſometimes they caſt their leaves, do keep it from going to ruine and mouldering away, to which the Prophet is ſuppoſed to allude. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6.13. I know <hi>Ahab</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the good <hi>Prophet</hi> as the <hi>troubler of Iſrael,</hi> who indeed was as the <hi>Chariot and Horſemen thereof</hi> for its ſecurity and defence. And he juſtly retorted that crimination upon <hi>Ahab</hi> himſelf. So in the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times, if there were War, Earthquakes, plague, inundations, the poor Chriſtians muſt to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as if they were the cauſe of it. When <hi>Aurelius</hi> upon experience found that they prevailed more by their prayers for the good of the Empire, than others could by prayers and arms, ſo that he deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the Senate to ceaſe their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution againſt them, leſt they ſhould turn thoſe ſpiritual wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons againſt the Empire, the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of which he had found in ſuch
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:50143:78"/>an eminent inſtance, and that they might pray for the good of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire. As <hi>Darius</hi> defired that the <hi>Jews might offer ſacrifice of ſweet ſavors unto the God of Heaven, and pray for the Life of the King, and of his Sons. Ezra.</hi> 6.10. Upon the ſame ground <hi>Juſtinian</hi> (as we may ſee <hi>Conſtit.</hi> 6. <hi>ad Epiphanium</hi>) took ſuch care for the eſtabliſhing of the true Religion, and for the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of thoſe ſacred Rules which were given by the Apoſtles as that which would conduce much to the happineſſe of the Empire, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for the ſetling of a pious Miniſtry, by whoſe prayers he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped for ſo great bleſſings upon himſelf and his Government. And a <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>great Prince</hi> in our own memory doth not only acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that natural influence which Religion hath upon the obedience of Subjects (whereof I have alittle before ſpoken) who himſelf doth beſt expreſſe his own ſence of it. <hi>It is no wonder</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if Men not fearing God, ſhould not honour their King. They will eaſily contemn
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:50143:78"/>ſuch ſhaddows of God, who reverence not that ſupream and adorable Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, in compariſon of whom all the Glory of Men and Angels is but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity,</hi> but as knowing alſo how far it doth conduce morally to the happineſſe of a Nation, gives it in charge to his Son (his Majeſty now reigning in <hi>England</hi>) <hi>to begin and end with God, and alwayes to keep up ſolid Piety, and thoſe fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal truths, which mend both the hearts and lives of Men, it being not only the Glory of Princes to advance Gods Glory, but the means to make them proſperous, and keep them from being miſerable.</hi> Whereupon his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> as remembring ſuch pious words and counſels of His <hi>Royal Father,</hi> did at his firſt reſtoration expreſſe his juſt diſpleaſure againſt ſuch, as pretending a great zeal to his Cauſe and Service, did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcredit it by the licence of their lives and manners; but ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the driving away thoſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching mercies, which they ſhould rather have acknowledged in their ſeveral ſtations, with cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:50143:79"/>integrity, and refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in their lives. It is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily ſaid,
<q>—Delirant Reges plectuntur Achivi.</q>
               </p>
               <p>But it is true on the other hand alſo, that Rulers are puniſhed for the ſins of the People. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.25. God ordering it ſo in his wiſe and righteous Providence; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as they partake many times in each others ſins, but as they have a joynt intereſt, ſo as one ſuffers in the ſufferings of another. I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member <hi>Machiavel</hi> (who was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought to be over-preciſe, or to be troubled with a bogling conſcience) complains of it in his <hi>Common-wealth,</hi> as that which he feared would be the ruine of <hi>Italy,</hi> 
                  <q>that wickedneſſe did ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound, and that there was ſuch a decay of Religion amongſt them, and they were ſo far de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generated from the purity of the Primitive times, that they had reaſon to expect the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance of God upon them. Whereupon he ſhews how neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary it is for Princes to have a
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:50143:79"/>ſpecial care for the preſervation of the purity of Religion,</q> which I am ſure is an innocent policy, and the wiſeſt <hi>maxim</hi> which he layes down: for beſides, that the Church hath alwayes been a <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſom ſtone, which hath broken in pieces all that have burdened them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with it,</hi> Zach. 12.13. Whilſt <hi>Righteouſneſſe doth exalt a Nation,</hi> Prov. 14.34. <hi>Wickedneſſe</hi> (like the talent of lead in the <hi>Ephah, Zach.</hi> 5.8.) <hi>ſinks</hi> it down. We know ten righteous perſons would have ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a <hi>Sodom,</hi> and God would do nothing againſt it, whilſt there was one in it. And if God did not for the ſake of ſuch, many times ſpare Nations, and ſhew them ſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar favour, there had been no ground for that which he himſelf hath pronounced of them, that they are ſuch, <hi>of whom the World is not worthy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:50143:80"/>
               <head>SECT. XIV. <hi>An enquiry into the cauſes, why Religion is ſo much neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected. The remoter cauſes the corruption of Mans na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the malice and power of the Devil, the nearer cauſe, the prevalenccy of ſence againſt Faith and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which is removed by ſhewing in how many in ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of our Lives, we do by reaſon correct the errors of ſenſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HE that ſhall read what I have hitherto written, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the general practice of the World, will perhaps wonder, that if theſe things be ſo, Men ſhould no better underſtand their own intereſt, but generally neglect this which is pretended to conduce ſo much to the making of the World happy, &amp; what I have ſaid, though it
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:50143:80"/>may ſeem to ſome to have ſome ſhew, of probability, will hardly obtain belief, but lye under ſome ſuſpition, like the honeſt projects of ſome well-wiſher to the publick good, which never obtained ſo much credit as to be reduced to tryal. Wherefore I ſhall a little enquire after the cauſes of that ungodlineſſe and prophaneneſſe, that ſo generally reigns in the World. And firſt, we know the Scripture hath oft taught us that the nature of Man is ſo corrupted by that which is called <hi>Original Sin, That the imaginations of the thoughts of his heart are only evil, and that continually, his heart deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately wicked and deceitful above all things;</hi> his underſtanding ſo dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened that he is <hi>alienated from the life of God, through the ignorance that is in him: filled withall unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; fleſhly luſts, warring againſt the Soul, and prevailing in our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to bring forth fruit unto Death. The Wiſdom of the fleſh is enmity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, ſo that</hi> man is <hi>wiſe to do evil, but he hath no knowledge to do
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:50143:81"/>good.</hi> Now experience doth more confirm us in the belief of this, than a thouſand Arguments. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, we oft read of the enmity of the Devil againſt Mankind, and though his power be not much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned by many, yet it is like the influence of Coeleſtial Bodies (Sun Moon and Stars) upon theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary things, powerful and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual, though not diſcerned but in the effects: hence we read of his <hi>working effectually in the hearts of the Children of diſobedience: of men being taken captive of him at his pleaſure: of the ſtrength of deluſion: of his going about like a roaring Lion:</hi> of <hi>wreſtling with principalities and powers: and reſiſting the Devil ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt in the Faith.</hi> He that ſhould have ſeen the Poor Man cured by Chriſt, offering violence to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and caſting himſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times into the fire, ſometimes into the water, would have eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded that he was acted by ſome evil ſpirit to ſuch things as were deſtructive to his own nature: ſo to ſee men ſin againſt their own ſouls,
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:50143:81"/>and run ſuch deſperate hazards a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their own intereſt, is a clear argument that they are acted by ſome other nature, which ſeeks their ruine and deſtruction. Now theſe may be remote cauſes of the prevalency of that <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> which we ſee and lament in the World, but yet there muſt be ſome nearer cauſes ſearched out; for (unleſſe it be in ſome ſecret <hi>Sympathies</hi> and <hi>Antipathies</hi>) <hi>Man</hi> doth ordinarily act according to reaſon, that is, what is either really ſo, or ſeems ſo to him, and there muſt be ſome <hi>ratio motiva</hi> to elicite, or draw forth the acts of his will. The Grace of God is powerful in good acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, yet it works congruouſly to our natures, moving by the means of ſome rational arguments and principles: ſo the efficacy of the Devil is very great in evil actions; yet he makes uſe for the moſt part of <hi>moral arguments,</hi> though he had ſuch a hand in <hi>Judas,</hi> his Treaſon, and <hi>Annanias</hi> his coſenage, as that he is ſaid <hi>to put theſe things into their hearts,</hi> yet, by the whole tenor of
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:50143:82"/>their ſtory, we find that there were ſome moral motives he made uſe of, and that it was covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that did more, immediately ſway in theſe ſins. Now (it ſeems) one main reaſon of Mens <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> which is more near and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, is the <hi>prevalency of ſenſe,</hi> as there are ſome actions, which do prevent the reaſonings of the mind, which we call <hi>actiones homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> but not <hi>humanae,</hi> which indeed are <hi>actions of Men,</hi> but not <hi>humane actions,</hi> proceeding from the eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial principle of man, objects coming to the ſenſe, before they can have acceſs to the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; the ſpirits move diſorderly till the underſtanding taking cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of the matter, do rectifie ſuch motions of the ſpirits: as in a ſudden noiſe or unexpected ſight, the ſenſes as the <hi>Centinels</hi> take the firſt alarm; but as ſoon as the news is carryed to the underſtanding, as the main guard or principal offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, and found to be of no dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequence, this ſudden commotion is allayed: ſo in more
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:50143:82"/>important paſſages of our lives, ſenſe makes many diſorderly ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies and motions, without taking counſel of the underſtanding, and objects do make very deep im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions upon them; and the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture doth take notice how much we are led by ſenſe in this frail ſtate, wherein we are ſo as we may all ſay with the Propher, <hi>Law.</hi> 3.51. <hi>Our eye affects our heart,</hi> this is the foundation of the Apoſtles ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.20. <hi>He that loveth not his Brother whom he hath ſeen, how can he love God whom he hath not ſeen?</hi> We have a thouſand times more reaſon to love God, than to love our Brother, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the perfections and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies that are in God, to render him amiable, and the obligations which we are under, to him who hath done more ten thouſand times for us than all the friends which we have in the World; but whatever reaſon there may be in the thing it ſelf, the Apoſtle argues according to our poor capacity, &amp; the acceſs that things have to us,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:50143:83"/>and doth clearly ſuppoſe that things which have acceſſe to out ſenſes, are more effectual for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving our affections, than ſuch things as are only the object of faith. So though we hear of an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Majeſty that created and ſuſtains our ſelves, and all other finite beings, who ſeeth all our actions, and will one day call us to an account for them; and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of an eternal weight of glory, made up of things, which <hi>eye hath not ſeen, nor ear heard, nor ever en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the heart of Man to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive:</hi> theſe things do not move us, becauſe they are far out of our ſight, and the things of the World which are nearer to our ſenſes, and are the immediate ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of them, pleaſing the <hi>taſt,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting the <hi>ſmell,</hi> tickling and flattering the <hi>Ear,</hi> dazling the <hi>eyes,</hi> have more prevalency upon us.</p>
               <p>But yet, upon examination we ſhall find this is not ſufficient to prevail againſt thoſe important conſiderations, which I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:50143:83"/>propoſed, nor to leave man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind excuſable for abandoning himſelf to the pleaſures of this life, ſo as to neglect thoſe better things which are propounded as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of holineſs. Let us but quit our ſelves like men, and exerciſe thoſe common principles of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, which we exerciſe in other affairs of our lives, and though we cannot perhaps thereby ſilence the clamors of ſence, yet we may confute them, and reject them. Do we not ordinarily ſee men correct the errors of ſenſe by reaſon? Do we not ſee them part with their blood, to prevent the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of a diſeaſe? which for the moſt part they do believe or ſuſpect, not upon the evident demonſtrations (but probable conjectures) of a Phyſician, or at beſt by their own reaſon. Do not men endure the cutting off of a member to ſave the body, and lengthen out a miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life for ſome days or years? Do not men drink the moſt unpleaſing potions for the recovery of their health, or repairing their decayed
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:50143:84"/>ſtrength? Do not men caſt their ſeed into the earth, in hopes of receiving the increaſe of it? Doth not the Merchant ſend away his goods, in hope to receive others for them, which may bring him ſome gain and advantage? And what is all this, to denying ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and worldly luſts? denying our ſelves the pleaſure of ſin, for the pleaſure of Heaven? yea, do we not ſee men ordinarily binding their Sons to ſome Apprenticeſhip, for many years, that ſo they may learn a Trade to maintain them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in ſome repute in the world, when they ſhall come to years? rather than let them live in idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and pleaſure, giving up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to childiſh ſports and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, when they are young, which would afterwards expoſe them to poverty and contempt. And he is accounted a cruel and unjuſt Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that will not thus love his Child, with ſuch a prudent ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, rather than undo him by a fooliſh indulgence; yet, how wide a difference is there in theſe caſes?
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:50143:84"/>And how far doth this fall ſhort of expreſſing the unreaſonableneſs of ſuch as will rather enjoy preſent pleaſures, than prepare for future happineſſe? A Child is bound to an Apprenticeſhip, and he perhaps dies before his time be out, and ſo all his labour and charge is loſt, or he doth not live ſeven years a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man after he hath lived ſeven years in a hard ſervice. But he that gives up himſelf to the ſervice of Chriſt, let it be imagined to be as hard as ſome mens prejudice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades them, the ſooner he dyes, the ſooner his ſervice is ended, and though he dye never ſo ſoon, he loſeth not his Freedom, but is made a Citizen of Heaven, and once entred there, he never dyes but doth for ever reap the fruit of his labours. Do we not give twenty times as much for the <hi>Fee-ſimple</hi> (as they ſpeak) of an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate as it will bring us in one year? and according to the ſame rule, were we ſure to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin twenty years, and could imagine them to be equal to
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:50143:85"/>the joyes of Heaven, yet we ſhould quit them for thoſe everlaſting pleaſures, which we ſhould enjoy for ever <hi>our ſelves;</hi> and not only for ſome Ages, as we hope to do Eſtates on Earth, not in our <hi>ſelves,</hi> but only in our <hi>poſterity.</hi> Further yet, we ſee it is in <hi>vain to lay a ſnare in the ſight of any Bird. Prov.</hi> 1.17. they will not come into the Net to feed, if they perceive it, or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the bait, when they ſee the hook: yet fooliſh men do venture on Hell, which they are told will certainly be the wages of ſin, and will enjoy the preſent pleaſures of it, though they have all the aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that a man can have of any thing which he ſees not with his eyes, that it will coſt him his life, and that his Soul muſt rue for ever in Hell. God indeed doth not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt himſelf to us ordinarily here, nor take us up as he did <hi>Paul</hi> into the third Heavens, to ſhew us the Glory thereof, but he will have us to exerciſe faith here, and to take his word, which he hath ſo fully confirmed to us, that we may as
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:50143:85"/>certainly truſt to it, as if we had the cleareſt evidence in the world. The Husband-man caſts his ſeed into the ground without any fear or ſuſpition of loſing, having been confirmed by many experiments in the hope of receiving it again with increaſe; but a thouſand ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periments will not ſo fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, as a divine teſtimony con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Covenants, Oaths and Seals, (the ordinary wayes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation amongſt men) ſo that a Divine faith, founded upon the word of God, is as <hi>the ſubſtance of things hoped for,</hi> which are but fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and makes them as it were really ſubſiſt, and is <hi>the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> confirming them to us, and as fully perſwading us of them, though they are not obvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to the ſenſe, as any Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phical demonſtration can confirm any truth, ſo that notwithſtanding the Apoſtle owns ſence to be a great means to move affections in this frail ſtate wherein we are, yet faith ſerves believers for a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent foundation of love and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:50143:86"/>
                  <hi>Though they ſee not Jeſus Chriſt, they love him, and rejoyce in him with joy unſpeakable and full of Glory.</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.7. We are ſhort ſighted, and <hi>cannot ſee a far off.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. but faith as a <hi>perſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> brings things nearer to us, that we may judge of them as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally preſent. Let not our <hi>ſenſes</hi> therefore uſurp authority over <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Reaſon,</hi> but lot Faith and Reaſon have their perfect work, let not the <hi>Men of the World be wiſer in their Generation than Children of light,</hi> let us not be wiſer in the things of the World, than in the things of Heaven. We chuſe not the faireſt of things, (for the moſt part) but ſuch as are more ſerviceable and durable, nor the ſweeteſt, but that which is wholſom and nouriſhing, we chuſe not the cleaneſt or pleaſanteſt way, but that which leads to the place which we are going to. So let us judge of things, not according as they preſent themſelves to our ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but as they have a real intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick worth to commend themſelves
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:50143:86"/>to our judgments, and let us not judge of things according to their ſuitableneſſe to our preſent fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but as they conduce to our abiding good, meaſuring every thing not by <hi>Time,</hi> but by <hi>Eternity.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XV. <hi>Inconſiderateneſſe, another great cauſe of Atheiſm, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which the beſt reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are a ſerious apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the great moment, and importance of ſpiritual things, frequent reading and hearing the word of God, Chriſtian communion and conference about matters of Religion, mutual admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The prevalency of evil cuſtoms and habits, the folly of deferring repentance.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>ANother chief reaſon of that Atheiſm, which abounds ſo
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:50143:87"/>much in the World is, <hi>inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſſe,</hi> the moſt important truths do not affect us any longer than we conſider them. The <hi>Platoniſts</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved this who made <hi>knowledge</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>remembrance,</hi> or an actual conſideration of that which Man knows, not reckoning that to be knowledge which lyes dead in the <hi>habit,</hi> and doth not at all affect the Soul. And we find that the Scripture layes much weight upon this <hi>conſideration</hi> or remembrance, yea, as much as Mans ſalvation comes to. We may obſerve, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.3. There is an <hi>Epimone,</hi> wherein the Prophet layes the ſin of <hi>Iſrael</hi> upon this, that they did not <hi>conſider.</hi> So 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 8.47. We may obſerve af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction brings men to bethink themſelves, that brings them to repentance, and repentance is a means to obtain pardon; and we find by experience, that when Men are by ſickneſſe brought to a ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous weighing of matters, they are eaſily perſwaded to make good promiſes and reſolutions, which when their minds are afterwards
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:50143:87"/>(by the pleaſures of the World) diverted from the thoughts of, they turn to their former courſe; yea, we ſee many times that Men are ſo ingenuous as to yield to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs, and to condemn them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and their own wayes, when they are admoniſhed of them, as if they ſtood in need of no more, but to be put in mind of ſuch things as they have in their own hearts, and only to have conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence awakened, and we find <hi>Ezek,</hi> 18.14.28. that the turning away of a wicked man, from the evil of his wayes, depends chiefly upon <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</hi> I have already ſhewed that the Devil is the remote cauſe of that wickedneſſe and prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which abounds in the World; yet, he uſeth this as the great means to draw Men from God, to divert their minds from the thoughts of ſuch things, as may have an influence upon <hi>their</hi> affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actions to make a change in them, as we ſee plainly in the <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>Sower.</hi> Luk. 8.12. <hi>Men hear the word, then comes the Devil
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:50143:88"/>and takes it away out of their hearts, leſt they ſhould believe and be ſaved.</hi> Firſt, we find by experience that M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n are oft ſeriouſly affected with thoſe things, that they hear while they are lively repreſented to their minds, and preſſed ſeriouſly upon their conſciences, preſently we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that their thoughts are quite taken off from thoſe things, and (like water which hath been warmed) they return to their old temper again. We ſee here Chriſt himſelf aſſigns the cauſe of it, it is the Devil that doth this, where it is ſuppoſed that he hath power to do it, though we are not ſo eaſily able to underſtand how he doth it, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be by propounding other objects to us. We ſee here his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign in it diſcovered, which is to hinder their <hi>believing,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently their <hi>Salvation,</hi> which we find by ſad experience to be the woful conſequent of this his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice. Now the moſt effectual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt this <hi>inconſiderateneſſe,</hi> would be a ſerious apprehenſion of the great moment and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:50143:88"/>of theſe things. It is the means which <hi>Moſes</hi> preſcribes to the <hi>Iſraelites, Deut.</hi> 32.47. for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their hearts to thoſe things, which he teſtified to them. <hi>It is not a vain thing for you</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>it is your life, and by thoſe things you ſhall prolong your dayes.</hi> It is a rule of Prudence which prevails throughout, that <hi>we ſhould look to the main chance,</hi> and not neglect the important affairs of our life. The Husbandman ſorgets many petty buſineſſes, but he never forgets to Plow and ſow. He would be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a mad man that ſhould go to the Market and buy trifles and toyes for his children, and forget to buy them bread. A Traytor will not forget to ſue out his pardon, or a Man that hath a ſuit for his whole Eſtate, forget to produce his evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences, and prepare his anſwer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Term.</hi> This is our caſe, we are condemned already in law, <hi>John</hi> 3.18. that is in force againſt us, we know not how ſoon we ſhall be ſetched to execution. If a Man did but apprehend the danger he is
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:50143:89"/>in continually, while he is a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, and in an unregenerate condition, ſtanding continually upon the pits brink, and ready to fall in, it would ſurely awake him out of his ſecurity, and prevent his ſleep, till he ſhould have ſome hope of his pardon, or the thoughts of the infinite advantage that true <hi>Godlineſs</hi> brings with it, would make him continually apply his heart to it. <hi>The abundance of the Rich, ſuffers him not to ſleep;</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his care and ſolicitude for the keeping of it, and we have more cauſe a thouſand times to be ſollicitous in this caſe, <hi>leſt a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and</hi> poſſibility <hi>being left us of entring into ſuch a reſt, we ſhould by any means fall ſhort of it.</hi> The ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the Goſpel, the reading of the Word, the Communion of the Saints are preſcribed by God, as a further remedy of this evil. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.13. Daily mutual exhortation is commended as a means to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the hardening of our hearts through the deceitfulneſs of ſin, which the more it is indulged, the
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:50143:89"/>more it inſinuates, and prevails upon us. Mens knowledge makes not the Word of God leſs uſeful to them; therefore it is a vain igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant thing for Men to neglect it, upon pretence of knowing as much as their Teachers: though the Saints to whom <hi>Peter</hi> writes, were inſtructed and eſtabliſhed in the truth, yet he thinks it neceſſary to write thoſe things to them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12. <hi>to put them in remembrance, and thereby to ſtir up their pure minds.</hi> Cap. 3.1. <hi>The words of the wiſe being not only as nails to faſten,</hi> that Chriſtians may be eſtabliſhed, <hi>but as goads</hi> to excite, that ſo they may not grow negligent, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.11. and the work of Miniſters lies more in awakening the conſcience, and quickening the affections, than informing the Judgement, and there are few men that live where the ſound of the Goſpel comes, but know, that which duely im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, would make a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble change in their lives, and I think it might be of ſingular uſe in a Chriſtian life, for thoſe that have
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:50143:90"/>near Relations (if ſuch as are prudent and faithful) or thoſe that have friends which are to them as their own Souls, if they live toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and have opportunity to know well each others converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeriouſly to oblige themſelves to each other, if they obſerve any thing in each others lives, or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages which is unbecoming their profeſſion, to take the firſt opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (with all Chriſtian meekneſs and privacy) to tell them of it, how they ſpake ſuch a thing unad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſedly, did this thing unſeemly, exceeded in the other thing. I know it is a duty of zeal and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which all Chriſtians owe to each other, but thoſe have the beſt opportunity for it, who have daily intimate converſation with others, and advantage for obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the whole procedure of their lives. And this which I have now been ſpeaking of doth likewiſe make that gracious Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, which the Goſpel re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires more neceſſary. And for this cauſe God did not only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:50143:90"/>it of the Jews, but further enjoyns them the uſe of their <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries,</hi> and the writing, the moſt important Periods of the Law, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Gates and Poſts, that ſo the things which did ſo nearly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern them, might be continually ſounding in their ears, and repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before their eyes. I might aſſign further, ſome other cauſes and cures of mens Atheiſm and wickedneſſe, as the corruption of mans nature doth ſtrongly incline a man to evil, ſo Regeneration is that which doth change their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and diſpoſe them to holineſs; but there are many acts of mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, which conduce to Mens pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent advantage, (both in a perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal and a relative capacity) to which regeneration is not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, and I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſpoken ſomething of it, Sect. 7. therefore I ſhall ſay no more of it in this place. Concerning the praevalency of evil habits, and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, and the prejudice that doth thereby ariſe againſt holineſs, as alſo concerning the advantage
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:50143:91"/>that one who is a Chriſtian indeed, (and hath experience of ſpiritual comforts, and the ſweetneſſe of the duties of Religion) hath above one that is only outwardly a Chriſtian, and doth duties only as a task, I have elſewhere ſpoken ſomewhat alſo, and ſo ſuperſede from any further conſideration of them. I confeſs, I think the putting off, and procraſtinating of repentance, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains many in the ſnares of Satan: but the former part of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe doth wholly militate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this folly of men, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive them of all ſuch pretence in that, (beſides the imprudence and extream madneſſe of putting off that which we know not whether we ſhall ever have opportunity for, and leaving a matter of ſuch importance, as our eternal Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at uncertainties) the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages which Men have by obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the precepts of the Goſpel, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in this life, do require our moſt ſpeedy applying our ſelves to the obſervance of them, and argue the deferring of our repentance of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:50143:91"/>the greateſt folly, and all that have been brought thereto, (eſpecially in their old age) have been ready with <hi>Auſtin</hi> to complain, that <hi>they have known God too late,</hi> &amp; repented that they did no ſooner exchange the pleaſures of ſin, for the joy and peace which is in believing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
               <head>SECT. XVI. <hi>Objections, from differences in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on anſwered, though we could not be fully aſſured that the Chriſtian Religion is true, yet it would be our wiſdom to obſerve the Rules and Precepts of it. The proofs which ſome have of the truth of Chriſtian Religion, clearer than thoſe which ſome deſire to have, &amp; clearer than any produced for the truth of any other Religion. Objections from the improbability and ſeeming contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of many things in Scripture anſwered. Notwithſtanding the difference amongſt Chriſtians, all of them are agreed, in ſo much as may ſerve for the well ordering of our converſations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are ſome yet that (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing to find any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:50143:92"/>for palliating their ſin) will ask how we ſhall find out the <hi>true Religion,</hi> amidſt ſo many differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as there are amongſt men about it. When we ſee men agreed and come to ſome accord, about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion we will conſider of the whole buſineſſe. Now to ſuch I anſwer, that if their doubt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that be the only true amongſt thoſe which are profeſſed in the <hi>world.</hi> Firſt, the eſteem which it hath obtained in the World, and the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence wherewith it hath been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in all places, to which the knowledge of it hath come, may challenge from any wiſe man the moſt ſerious weighing of what is offered for the proof of it, which I will not here ſtand to ſum up, but will only ſay, (and that with much confidence) that whoſoever ſhall but ſeriouſly peruſe what hath been written in ſeveral Ages, for evincing the truth of it, will (ſee at leaſt) ſo much probability for the truth of it, and ſo much reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleneſſe and equity in the precepts of it, that they will account it
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:50143:92"/>madneſſe in any to run the hazard of loſing that reward, which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds, or ſuffering the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which it threatens to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſers of it, rather than ſubmit to a <hi>Law</hi> ſo <hi>holy,</hi> ſo <hi>juſt,</hi> ſo <hi>good.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe it, many prove falſe, yet, what would Men loſe thereby? indeed they would loſe their fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture reward, but they would have the preſent advantage of it, for (as <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> truly ſays, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Scil.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>The way of ſin is more difficult than the way of holineſſe.</hi> And I cannot but here ſubjoyn the ſaying of a Learned Man, on <hi>Mat.</hi> 11.29. <hi>Precepta Chriſti, talia ſunt ut ſi par ponatur conſuetudo unius hominis ad reciè vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vendum, alterius ad flagitia, non dubie multo dulcior ſit futura vita quaeſecundum virtutem eſt, graviſſima enim tributa pendunt qui ambitioni, qui avaritiae, qui libidini ſerviunt:</hi> that is, <q>Suppoſe ſeveral Men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually accuſtomed to a ſinful, and a Holy life, and the way of Vertue and Piety ſhall be found to be much more pleaſant, and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:50143:93"/>thoſe that are Vaſſals to ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Covetouſneſs, ſenſuality will find the tribute heavy, which they pay to ſuch Tyrants.</q> So that as thoſe who ſearch into the ſecrets of nature to find out the <hi>Philoſophers Stone,</hi> though they attain not their end, yet find out many ſecrets and experiments, which may be pleaſing and uſeful: in like manner, thoſe who ſeek e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal happineſs in the Goſpel, though it ſhould be ſuppoſed that they may miſs of it, yet they ſhall find ſuch real advantage by the obſervation of thoſe precepts, that are there given, that their labour would not be in vain, but they would be ſufficiently recompenced for it. But now ſuppoſe, the things therein delivered, ſhould prove true, what a woful caſe would thoſe be in, which ſhould be found to be neglecters of it? what a dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful thing would it be for them to <hi>fall into the hands of the living God?</hi> and you that think good to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend your belief of the truth of the Goſpel, that ſo you may without
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:50143:93"/>diſturbance enjoy the pleaſures of ſin, and prevent the clamors of an unquiet accuſing Conſcience. Gird up your loyns like Men, and tell me, (I beſeech you) do the arguments which you have againſt the truth of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> as far exceed in probability, thoſe which are alledged for the proof of it, as the Glory which it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds (as the reward of holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) exceeds the pleaſures of ſin, (ſuppoſing that pleaſure in it which you imagine) or as far as the torments threatned, as the wages of ſin exceed the utmoſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity that men can be imagined to ſubmit themſelves to, in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Goſpel? yea, let men but act congruouſly, and allow as much in matters of Religion, as in other inſtances of their lives, and we ſhall find that, as the Chriſtians of old argued againſt the Heathens, that they believed many things in Philoſophy, and humane learning, upon leſſe evidence than what was offered for the proof of Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſo men do make much greater
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:50143:94"/>adventures upon more improbable grounds than any they can be ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined to make by conforming themſelves to the Rules of the Goſpel, upon the grounds laid down for confirmation of it. And if men were as ſuſpicious and wary in other things as theſe <hi>Scepticks;</hi> in matters of Religion, they muſt not eat, leſt through the malice or negligence of ſome, there ſhould be poyſon mingled with their meat; they muſt not go into an houſe, leſt it ſhould fall upon their heads; they muſt not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey any commands of their Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, unleſs they ſhould come and deliver them in expreſſe words to themſelves, becauſe ſome might poſſibly counterfeit their hands and ſeals; yea, it is moſt evident, that they muſt forbear ſo many things, that they would not be ſit for converſe with men, but would quite overthrow human Society. Let me go a little further, I deſire (in good earneſt) to know of Men, what evidence they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire to perſwade them of the
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:50143:94"/>truth of Chriſtian Religion, and it may be what they have already will be found more convincing. Some may fancy a voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven would ſatisfie them. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, they have already a <hi>more ſure word of Prophecy.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. They think perhaps if one ſhould come from the other World, of their former acquaintance, and tell them what is done there, they ſhould believe; but he that doth not believe the Scriptures, <hi>will not believe though one ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from the dead.</hi> Luk. 16.31. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther do I beg the queſtion, in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging theſe things from Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, grounding them wholly on its authority, but aſſert them bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>theorems,</hi> which are demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrable by reaſon, being aſſured that there might be more objected againſt ſuch kind of evidence, than is to be objected againſt that which is brought in the Scriptures. For tell me, I beſeech you, in caſe there ſhould be ſuch a voice from Heaven, might we not as eaſily ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that our ſenſes might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:50143:95"/>or that it might be form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the air by ſome ſpirit, as ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that we ſhould be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the Prophets who wrought ſo many miracles, for the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their miſſion from God, which ſo plainly fore-told many things to be accompliſhed after many Ages, which could not be foreſeen in their cauſes, that were holy men, and ſuch as could not be imagined to have a deſign to deceive, eſpecially the <hi>things</hi> which they delivered, being ſuch as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed them to danger and trouble and were not likely to bring them any advantage in the World. Or ſhould <hi>Moſes,</hi> or one of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, or Apoſtles ariſe from the dead &amp; tell us, they did indeed live here upon the earth in ſuch times, and preach ſuch Doctrine, and work ſuch miracles; yea, and they have found ſince their Death, that thoſe things which they Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecyed, or Preached, are true, they ſee thoſe who obeyed their word triumphing in Heaven, and thoſe who contemned it, torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:50143:95"/>in Hell: might we not as eaſily ſuſpect that this might be ſome Spirit, which appeared in their ſhape to delude us, as that the <hi>Jews</hi> who are Enemies to the <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> ſhould deviſe a writing and diſperſe it abroad in the World, which ſhould ſo plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirm the <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> as the <hi>Old Teſtament</hi> doth, which is at this day owned among the <hi>Jews,</hi> or that thoſe Antient Writers ſhould conſpire together, to deceive the World, in recording the ſame things, which we find in Scripture, or that the Scriptures ſhould be tranſlated into ſo many languages, and diſperſed all the World over, ſo ſoon after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, and none be ſo falſe to the divulgers of it, or ſo true to the World, as to give notice of it, if it were a forgery, or that theſe things ſhould be recorded in the <hi>Roman Regiſters,</hi> and the acts of their Senate to which <hi>Tertullian</hi> durſt appeal, if there had been no ſuch thing? This one thing would I learn, ſhould one come to us, as
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:50143:96"/>from the dead in the likeneſſe of <hi>Alexander, Caeſar, William</hi> the Conqueror, <hi>Wickliff, Luther, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin,</hi> and tell us in ſober ſadneſſe that they were ſuch a one, that lived in ſuch a time, did ſuch things, Preached ſuch Doctrine, whether ſhould we believe ſuch a Teſtimony ſooner than the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous conſent of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, and thoſe Books and Writings which are generally re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived as the works of ſuch Men? If any ſhall ſay that <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> are as confident of the truth of that Religion which they were brought up in, as we are of the truth of ours. I anſwer, they have not like ground for their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, as for the <hi>Heathens,</hi> what became of their <hi>Gods,</hi> their <hi>Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> when the <hi>Hebrew Child</hi> was born, and when the Goſpel began to ſpread in the World? Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the miracles wherewith o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Religions have been confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, with thoſe wherewith the Goſpel hath been confirmed, and ſee whether they be ſo many, ſo
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:50143:96"/>confeſſedly above the power of Nature or Art, ſo evidently, wrought in the ſight of all, as thoſe whereby the <hi>Chriſtian Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> hath been confirmed. What is the reaſon that the <hi>Turks</hi> admit no enquiry, or diſpute about matters of Religion, but require an implicite Faith? <hi>Truth ſeeks no corners, error ſhuns the light.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Laws of <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans</hi> whether there be that <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Equity, Wiſdom, conſonancy to right reaſon,</hi> and the <hi>light</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> in them which is to be found in the Scriptures. Examine the ways and means by which they have been propagated, whether they have reached any further than their Swords have made way for them, whether the <hi>Weapons of their warfare were ſpiritual or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal:</hi> whereas the Goſpel pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed through the evidence and power of the Spirit againſt the pretended authority of the <hi>Jews,</hi> the Wiſdom and learning of the <hi>Grecians,</hi> the power and force of the <hi>Romans,</hi> and Fiſhermen were
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:50143:97"/>too hard for <hi>Rabbies, Philoſophers, Judges, Generals, Armies.</hi> If any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the improbability of ſome things delivered in Scripture, I ſhall only propound whether there be not ſome things which we are fully aſſured of, either by <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> or <hi>Mathematical demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which to others ſeem as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probable as any thing in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture ſeems to us, and ſhall we not grant God to be as much wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than our ſelves, as we are wiſer than other Men, and ſuppoſe he could as eaſily convince us of thoſe things which now ſeem impoſſible to us, as we can convince others of thoſe things which they cannot at preſent believe? And if the ſeeming contradictions that are in Scripture be urged to weaken the authority of them, they are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an argument of the integrity and ſincerity of the Penmen, and their leaving things ſo ſecurely, which do not at firſt ſight ſeem to accord with other Scriptures, ſhews clearly they had no Plot to deceive the World, otherwiſe they
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:50143:97"/>would have conſpired to make their teſtimonies, agree in words more exactly; yet upon examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the matter, and conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſeveral circumſtances of time, place, Perſons, ſcope, occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the ſeveral uſes of the ſame word and phraſe, the latitude which all Authors uſe in their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, the ſeveral places and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the ſame name, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral names given to the ſame place or Perſon, the ſhortneſſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, Hiſtory, and ſupplying in one place, what is wanting in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, the attending rather to ſence and ſubſtance, than to words and phraſes in citing Scripture, we ſhall find that there is a very fair accord between thoſe places which ſeem to be at the greateſt variance, and if we cannot recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile all places, yet if we conſider that we have by attending to ſuch things as I have mentioned al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, compoſed ſo many ſeeming differences, we may conclude it is from our own ignorance, that we cannot compoſe the reſt, and that
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:50143:98"/>there is yet ſomewhat elſe that we are ignorant of, which if we could find out, we might as eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile the reſt, which at preſent ſeem moſt irreconcilable, and it is obvious to every one how many difficulties and contradictions ſeem to be in every Science, while Men are but ſmatterers in it, which preſently vaniſh as ſoon as they come more perfectly to underſtand it. But now if this objection be framed againſt the differences which are among Chriſtians, which profeſſe the Goſpel, I will by the way obſerve this, that differences do moſt abound, where men (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſerious apprehenſions of the weight and importance of the matters of faith) do diligently apply themſelves to underſtand themſelves, the myſteries of the Goſpel, and to ſee with their own eyes, being affraid to be deceived in matters of ſuch moment, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the teſtimony of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and unwilling to loſe their Souls and Heaven, and God, to ſave the labour of ſearching after
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:50143:98"/>truth, and in thoſe Nations where I have had opportunity to be converſant, I have found moſt differences amongſt them, which have been moſt addicted to Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and moſt ſollicitous about the condition of their ſouls, and moſt agreement amongſt them, which have contented themſelves to follow others by an implicit faith, without troubling them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves much to ſearch after truth, and where there hath been ſuch a coldneſſe and indifferency in matters of Religion, that all have quietly accorded together, as the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> obſerve, that cold doth congregate <hi>Heteroge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neal</hi> things, or ſuch things as are of different kinds, making them all to conſiſt quietly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which heat doth ſever and ſeperate. So that I am almoſt ready to ſay with <hi>Luther,</hi> that <hi>I know not how to believe, that the Goſpel hath been preached in a place, where I do not ſee errors and diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> And it is further obſervable as an argument of the general con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:50143:99"/>of all Chriſtians, in the belief of the neceſſity, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of an holy life, that ſetting aſide ſome few, who (being them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Slaves to vile affections) have laid down ſome looſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to patronize their own cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt practiſes, and draw after them ſuch as are laden with the like ſinful luſts: men of all opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and perſwaſions have earneſtly preſſed men to the greateſt ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and accurateneſſe in their converſations, and have ſerved themſelves at leaſt of a ſhew of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, as the moſt effectual means to induce men to a belief of their Doctrine. But to come nearer to the matter, let us leave men to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend their belief a while of thoſe things, which they ſee controverted, and where they find probable arguments alledged on the one ſide, and on the other, yet their objection holds not againſt ſuch things, wherein all are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, as are moſt of the precepts of the Goſpel. That rule which was formerly mentioned, given by
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:50143:99"/>our Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly allowed by all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but by the very <hi>Heathens. Alexander Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verus</hi> did ſo much eſteem it, that he would have it written upon the Walls of his Palace. So many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther important truths, which are a ſufficient Foundation, of the moſt ſtrict and holy converſation are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed on amongſt all, as Gods <hi>om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſciency</hi> overſeeing all our actions, a <hi>future judgement,</hi> wherein all muſt be ſentenced according to their actions, inſomuch that even Robbers, and ſuch as conſpire in wickedneſſe, and ſeem to bid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance to Heaven, are ſelf condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and witneſſe for God againſt themſelves, in obliging themſelves to ſecreſie and faithfulneſſe to each other, by ſolemn oaths wherein they ſwear by the name of that God, whoſe commands they live in the open breach of, and ſo acknowledge him as a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſpectator of their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and one who will ſeverely puniſh the contempt of his autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in the breach of ſuch oaths.
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:50143:100"/>Many cannot agree indeed about methodizing their notions, and diſpoſing them into ſuch a <hi>ſyſteme</hi> as that every part may agree, and that there may be an harmony in the whole. Some cannot agree a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the <hi>order and nature of Gods decrees,</hi> yet all believe that no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree doth excuſe a Mans ſin, or that any can pretend any benefit by their election, that have not ſome evidence of it in their ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Men differ in their notions about the <hi>cauſe of ſin,</hi> yet on both ſides they hold; that as the kind of fruit is not according to the root or ſtock, but according to the Graft or Cyon, out of which it immediately grows: ſo the ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of actions depends not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on any remote cauſes which may have an influence into them, but upon the will of him that is the immediate cauſe of them, and that there is nothing in the decrees of God, or the temptations of Satan, which will excuſe the ſinner, or quit him from guilt. Men are at variance about the <hi>extent of the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:50143:100"/>of Chriſts death,</hi> but agree that none ſhall have any ſaving benefit by it, but thoſe that believe. Men differ about the <hi>Power of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and <hi>liberty of the will,</hi> but on both hands, own ſo much power as will leave men inexcuſable, and may be a ground of our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, and ſo much neceſſity of Grace and Divine aſſiſtance, as may bring us upon our knees, and force us to our Prayers. Some dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference there is about <hi>Perſeverance,</hi> but a conſent in this, that he that doth not perſevere in holineſs ſhall never be ſaved. Some difference there is about the <hi>hand that works have in our juſtification,</hi> but all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree that they are neceſſary in thoſe that are juſtified. Men vary in their opinions about <hi>the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law, the nature of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of Grace, Chriſtian liberty,</hi> &amp;c. but in this they conſent, that the things required in the Law are neceſſary to be done, though not perfectly, yet ſincerely as we can: that the Covenant of Grace is not ſo far abſolute, that men may be
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:50143:101"/>ſaved without faith and holineſs: that Chriſtians are not to abuſe their liberty, as an occaſion to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenciouſneſs. <hi>Now happy is he that condemns not himſelf in the things which he alloweth.</hi> In ſhort, let us pray as if all depended wholly on Gods grace, without our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors. Do <hi>good works,</hi> as if we were to be juſtified by them. Truſt to Gods Grace, and mercy in Chriſt, as if we had done no works at all. <hi>Live</hi> as if there were no <hi>Goſpel. Hope</hi> as if there were no <hi>Law.</hi> (I ſpeak not in reſpect of the lowneſs and ſervileneſs of our principles, but in reſpect of the diligence of our en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours) Let us walk watchfully and cautiouſly, as if we feared fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away; yet love God, and hope in him, as if we were certain to perſevere. In ſhort, (if I may take liberty to mention ſuch names) let us <hi>pray</hi> like <hi>Calviniſts, endeavour</hi> like <hi>Arminians, act</hi> like <hi>Legaliſts, hope</hi> like <hi>Antinomians;</hi> be <hi>Papiſts</hi> in our <hi>works, Proteſtants</hi> in our <hi>Faith.</hi> Let me again add, to prevent miſtake and offence, I ſpeak not of the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:50143:101"/>of Mens actions, but the matter and ſubſtance of them: nor of what they do in <hi>Hypotheſi,</hi> which come under ſuch diſtinguiſhing names, but, of what ſuch Mens principles do really (or at leaſt are ſuppoſed by others to) lead them to. Finally, <hi>whereto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us mind the ſame things.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:102"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 6. line 8. read <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. l. 11. <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.19. <hi>p.</hi> 34. <hi>l.</hi> 25. for God <hi>read</hi> Gold, <hi>p.</hi> 37. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>r. Col.</hi> 3.23. <hi>p.</hi> 51. <hi>l.</hi> 15. blot out <hi>Mankind, l.</hi> 28. blot out <hi>yet, p.</hi> 53 <hi>l.</hi> 15. for them <hi>r.</hi> him, <hi>p.</hi> 58. <hi>l.</hi> 10. <hi>r.</hi> out of joyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 129. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>r.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>p.</hi> 145. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>r. Zech.</hi> 12.3. There are ſome ſmall faults in the pointing, but ſuch as will not much trouble any Reader.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:50143:102"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
